[Music]
Hey.
Heat. Heat.
[Music]
Hello everybody. Good evening, good day
to everyone. I hope you're all doing
great and welcome to this latest episode
of the Ask Bij show. Today we discuss
geopolitics. This is the second live
stream I'm doing today. We're going to
discuss geopolitics. But let's see first
of all who was who all is there on the
live chat with us this fine evening
here. I can see I'm artistic maven
Rashmir is heartbroken. What happened?
What happened? Rashm what happened?
Heartbroken not sure. Uh okay let's see
who is who else is there? Mystic SK Sait
Jaredi Autonomous Scientist The
knowledge priest Vikash PJ Amya Tuli
from Germany. Good evening Rohit Kalita
geopolitical d from indor beneath bin
ray
I'm imatistic arpita shukla shashank
koshik hunter kenve shreas mitra achal
verma avin Vladimir Putin Aayush Singh
Vadhim manar srishi rohit kalita adi
vinay ray pritesh wakil pri shivi adi
rud
shashank koshik again shivas Sai Saita
ready Abin Priyange David Swanson
satellite
who else do we have we have Adit here we
have patriotic we have godliness Rishit
Agiraa Baron Zemo Somi Jane from Jaipur
patriotic the creator of existence is
here well oo is here achal vhapesh
rashmi says time peri
documents verification
n
okay I'm sorry to hear that something
has gone wrong with you but I hope
everything goes I think uh I hope you
able to fix that
uh Aayush Singh Bi Vikas PJ Abijit is
here Jay the knowledge priest Shreas
Mitra from Moscow
uh Srishi again polar bear Anand Pay
Yogesh Kumar Dbakar world Achala Abin of
Nigi Arjun
General Subutai Shesh Nik Vikash PJ and
everybody else. Danush Yogesh Binit Jay
Guman from Mal in Canada. Raja Akash
Kumar
and everybody else. All right.
Uh okay. So let us Binit is from
Siliguri. Good to see you sir. Adita and
everybody everyone else. Okay. We shall
take a bunch of questions. Before that,
I have a small announcement. In case
some of you are not aware, I have
finally started writing books. Finally
started publishing. Writing a book takes
a lot of time. It's a pretty arduous,
tedious effort. It takes months or
years. So, what I'm doing is I'm
whatever I'm writing, I'm serializing
the content. And I'm putting out each
chapter as an installment. So, I'm
writing a book on black holes. I think
black holes are very mysterious, very
interesting to a lot of people, but
people don't know what black holes are.
And black holes are explained in very
scientific terminology. So I am writing
about black holes in a way that everyone
can everyone can understand. So one of
these is about black holes. Here is the
thing dark stars to black holes. That's
the first installment. It's out. It's
come out about 48 hours ago. That's one
that I'm writing. And another one is a
series of short fiction
supernatural stories based in Indian
culture and civilization and mythology.
So this is another one. These are all
available on Amazon Kindle for now. Once
it is uh once I have published the
entire series of chapters for the back
holes book and a whole set of stories
for this mirrors of Maya series, then I
shall have them published in hard copy
format as well. But right now it's
available on on Amazon. So in case
you're interested, please go ahead and
acquire the books. If you read the
books, please leave honest reviews. That
will help me help me a lot. Help an
Indian writer. to help an Indian writer
who is not mentally colonized and trying
to do something good. All right, so
that's the announcement. Thank you so
much. I really appreciate everyone's
support. A lot of you have sent very
very nice messages in support. I really
appreciate all of you. I can't respond
to all of you individually, but thank
you so much for all the support. It
really means a lot to me. Now with that
said, let us get going with the
questions that we have today. So I'll
take u
super chat questions. First of all let's
see we have Saiti who says is Africa the
next global battleground? Is Africa the
next global battleground? So Africa is
not the next global battleground.
There's a battleground. There's going to
be competition in Africa uh when it
comes to the major powers. The Americans
and the French have historically been
the major powers in Africa. The French
in the Sahel region in West Africa,
Americans, the United States has
essentially vasalized the whole of
Africa either directly or indirectly.
And the Chinese have been entrance in
the past 15 or so or 15 20 years in
Africa in a variety of ways through
their uh development projects through
their various port strategies and so on.
And Russia is also a um a participant in
the geopolitical game in Africa. They
are active in the Sahel region. I
earlier they were active through the
Wagner group and now a little more
directly India to some extent is also
there in Africa. So there is indeed a
case for Africa is a global battleground
and it is to a large extent a global
battleground but not the largest global
battleground. The largest global battle
battleground now is Eurasia more more
actually Asia
because uh in Eurasia we have the
Ukraine situation going on. The
Americans wanted to essentially destroy
Russia through the Ukraine conflict. It
had it it has not worked
and then the effort is now on from the
American perspective to contain India.
The containment efforts towards China
are have already been going on for some
time. Now the objective is to contain
India as well. So actually it's Asia,
it's the Indian Ocean region, the the
so-called Indopacific region that is the
larger battleground. But Africa is also
a battleground which will uh and it will
be contested between the United States
to some extent France perhaps a little
bit and also China and Russia and to
some extent India
godliness says for the Indian state
after so much abuse open support to
Pakistan 50% tariffs no trade deal
choking India like China on
semiconductors equals to comprehensive
global strategic partnership uh I'm not
sure what's the angle of the Indian
state there but okay let's talk about
this you're talking about the India US
relationship obviously so
Mr. Trump a couple of days ago he said a
few nice words right Indian media has
reported and covered that extensively
the the nice things that Trump said in
response to someone's question during a
press interaction so he said that you
know India is a friend of ours and I
have a great friendship with with Prime
Minister Modi and that sort of thing a
few nice words briefly he said and he
also and this was this was reported in
the media and Prime Minister Modi
responded immediately to that saying
that we value the US partnership and we
look forward to continuing that
something to that effect. Prime Minister
Modi said something nice in a diplomatic
way immediately. So all these all this
time the past few months it's all been a
barrage of abuse from Trump and his
minions and from the Trump regime
right aimed at Prime Minister Modi aimed
at India because India has refused to
cave in. Prime Minister Modi has refused
to make India a US vasal and all this
abuse kept coming towards India and
Prime Minister Modi kept quiet. He
stayed silent about this mature silence.
Don't respond to provocations. The
moment Mr. Trump said something reason
kind of nice, Mr. Modi responded
immediately to that. So I think that's
very mature diplomacy from Prime
Minister Modi. But is it that now there
is going to be a truce between India and
the US? Is there now going to be an
off-ramp given to India and everything
is going to be back on track? Absolutely
not. And a lot of Indian commentators
are say have jumped to the conclusion
that yes, a new phase has started. India
and the US are now going to be friends
again. There's going to be a truce.
There's going to be some kind of uh u
better a phase of better relations and
Trump and Modi are friends again. That
sort of thing. that is incredibly
staggeringly naive. I mean I don't have
the words to describe how naive Indians
are. A few throwaway words of flattery
and oh Indians are dancing on the
streets. Yes, everything is fine again.
Extremely naive
analysis, very naive behavior. Very
childish behavior. That's how easy
Indians are to fool.
Okay. So the relationship hasn't
changed. The US priority is now going to
be to contain India. A containment
policy, a set of strategies aimed at
containing India and that's going to
continue.
Pakistan, the US is going to support
Pakistan essentially to the hilt. Okay.
Mr. Trump himself is personally invested
in Pakistan. His business empire is
invested in Pakistan. And then there's
the 50% tariffs and there's no trade
deal and there's the u there's the
demand that we open up our market
entirely to the US including the
agricultural sector everything which
will essentially destroy India's
industries if we do that right so that's
the situation and there's the
geopolitical angle also we Indian
analysts like to speak about the Chinese
string of pearls they've been speaking
about this for the past 20 25 years the
Americans have are creating are
constructing a ring of thorns around
India that There is East Pakistan, there
is West Pakistan, both are US vasals.
East Pakistan, Bangladesh is now going
to send apparently troops to Ukraine. So
they will get the training to fight and
then they will come back to Bangladesh
and that will in the future possibly
potentially if required be deployed
against India. Right? So India is being
encircled East Pakistan, West Pakistan,
the situation in Myanmar, the project K
Cookie Land for Christ project that the
Americans have set off. Yeah, that's
also has it stopped? Has it stopped at
all? So that's the situation. So the
relationship has not changed. Those who
are saying that that Trump has said some
nice words and Mr. Modi responded, it
means that everything is back on track.
That is so incredibly immature. That's
what we have to remember.
Words words don't matter. Actions only
matter. A few nice words doesn't make
any difference.
Ritik P is asking a question from
history. Now,
who are the top five greatest military
commanders in the past 20 years 10,000
years history? Listen, we are discussing
geopolitics. Sir, today this
episode is a geopolitics episode. We're
going to discuss geopolitics.
So, let's let's stick to geopolitics.
Please, if I start taking history
questions and other questions, then the
people who have come here to see
geopolitics, to understand geopolitics,
because I've said this is a geopolitics
episode, I'll be doing them a huge
disservice by taking questions from
outside of geopolitics. So, I I
apologize, but I will only take
questions about geopolitics today.
Apologies, Retik G, please sir, let's do
geopolitics today.
ICMBBS says what can India do
differently to better leverage soft
power literacy media culture
specifically in Southeast Asia Africa
Latin America even the west what can
India do differently what I'll tell you
India should do differently
focus on hard power
Indians have this obsession with soft
power
we need to develop our hard power. Soft
power means a big fat zero if you have
no hard power.
Please understand this. Please every day
wake up in the morning and remind
yourself soft power is zero if you don't
have hard power. I don't care about soft
power right now. What India should do
internally is a lot. We need to
prioritize our culture, our
civilization.
Literacy. We we are a nation of literate
people who can sign their names and who
can read and write. Is that literacy?
For proper literacy, we have to reform
the education system. Well, that's not
going to happen anytime soon. It's clear
media. Well, the Indian media is a bunch
of vasals who parrot the western
speaking lines or the or the talking
points given to them by whoever master
they serve. Is there an Indian
perspective in the Indian media?
If you see the coverage of the Ukraine
war, the first two three years, the
first two years especially, it was
simply they'll go and read something
from the west media and then they'll
parrot that in Hindi or whatever
language essentially portraying the west
as the as the as the uh you know the
side that is on the right side and the
the Russians as the aggressors. The
media it needs to look media essentially
is a paid media. Okay, more or less I'm
sure there are some media houses that
are completely entirely beautifully
independent. But most media is just
propaganda. It's all narrative. Culture,
we need to do a lot about culture.
If if you really want to talk about soft
power, India has the potential to be
a tourism superpower, a culture super
cultural superpower. Culture brings in
tourism. What are we doing about it? The
city of Bangkok gets more visitors,
foreign visitors than the whole of
India.
France, Spain, Mexico, these countries
get like 10, 20, 30, God knows how many
times more foreign visitors than India
tourists.
We can do so much. We can do a lot.
There's a lot we can do. But first,
let's focus on hard power. Hard power is
what? Economic and military power.
Nothing else.
Abishek says, why is the government not
investing in servers, building data
centers? I think only the government can
answer. uh see data is very important.
Technological sovereignty is is critical
to India to any nation like India who
wants to stand on its own and not cave
in and become a vasal of the US. So if
you don't want to become a an American
vasal then you need to do you need to be
sovereign in all important sectors
economic sovereignty we have it.
Military sovereignty we have it. Uh when
it comes to legislative and policy
sovereignty we have it. When it comes to
sovereignty over your territory, we have
it. But what about technological
sovereignty where everything depends on
the west huge issue that the government
needs to look into very seriously. Of
course, the government is taking action.
We have the semiconductor project going
on the semiconductor mission. We're
going to be producing our own chips that
may be 15 years behind the cutting edge
today, but we got to start somewhere.
So, I appreciate that and I applaud
that. But we need to be completely
self-reliant in everything. We need to
have our own social media that will
allow the country to stay in touch with
the with the with the people with each
other. We need to have our own social
media apps. We need to have our own all
of this. The entire technological stack
needs to be entirely indigenous because
you can't rely on foreign powers and
what they give you right for their own
purpose and for their own benefit. So
the government needs to look into this
and there needs to be a comprehensive
mission for this. So I agree with you
sir.
Teen talks dharma says Putin and she
talking about immortality. Well I am I
really have they I haven't seen that sir
I haven't seen any piece of news that
says that they are now planning to
become im immortal.
Don't know about that.
Okay.
Anonymous scientist says forecast for
India US relations and purchasing your
ebooks. First of all thank you so much
for for that. Thank you. Forecast for
India US relations. Um it's no longer
going to be a strategic partnership.
Look, after what the Americans did in
the wake of operation Synindur, all
strategic trust has evaporated. Whatever
little strategic trust existed
towards the US from India is gone.
It's gone. It's very clear that the US
is not a reliable friend, ally, partner,
whatever you want to call it. Strategic
partnership. What strategic partnership?
When you are aiding and abetting India's
number two enemy, Pakistan.
Hm. What strategic partnership? What
they want is a slave. What they want is
a nation like India becoming a Japan.
That sort of thing. That's what they
want. The Americans are the are the same
people as the British, aren't they? The
British had the East India Company. Now
the Americans want to create East India
India Company 2.0.
That's what they want to do.
And the US now realizes that it's very
clear that the Indian economy is going
to keep growing no matter what happens.
There's zero stand chance of recession
which means that in 20 years time India
could be a 10 15 god knows what trillion
dollar economy and and at that scale a
nation like India from the US
perspective is a threat. So they want to
ensure this doesn't happen which means
that they will do everything it takes to
contain India and to hamper India's
growth and progress and do everything it
takes to fragment India to fracture
India create all kinds of divisions in
India whatever division divisions the
British have left behind they will
augment the divisions and they will want
to de facto balkcanize India so that is
the forecast for the India US
relationship is going to be a very
u rough period the US is no longer are
going to act as a at least even even
pretend to act like a friend. Uh we
don't I don't care what a what few words
are said here and there. Oh, we are
friends and we've got a great relation.
Who cares about the words? What are your
actions? Only the actions matter. So the
forecast for the India US relationship
is that the US is going to continue its
policy and strategy multiple strategy
set of strategies to contain India and
it's going to be tough for India as a
consequence.
Amisha says, "Can GST reforms offset the
impact of Trump's tariffs?" Well, it
certainly is possible. See, first of
all, India and the US, we don't have the
biggest trade relationship.
We don't export a lot to the US. What 90
billion dollars a year? That's that's
not a whole lot in the larger scheme of
things.
And India apparently has a trade surplus
with the US which means that we export
more than we import from the US. So that
so we are the major we are the net
beneficiaries essentially that what's
that's what it means. Now if the US is
imposing 50% tariffs it means that it
will be very hard for India to export
stuff to the US goods to the US and
that's going to cause problems. So the
amount of the volume of goods and
services we export to the US volume in
US dollar terms will reduce that's the
obvious implication of that. So what do
we do then? So if you want to become a
manufacturing power which is very
important we will have to look for
alternative markets maybe the EU market
maybe Russia maybe something else we'll
have to look into this. The other
alternative is that we become a
consumption-driven economy. We we
manufacture for ourselves for our own
population. 1.4 billion people. We have
a lot of people who need a lot of goods,
services, whatever, consumer items,
whatnot. We manufacture for our own
economy, for our own population. That
can boost the economy, right? As long as
somebody is buying what's being
manufactured, whether it's outside
India, inside India, doesn't matter. The
GDP grows, the economy grows, it gets
stronger, more robust. So, you can
become you can do that by becoming a
consumption-driven economy. But for
that, you need to boost the spending
power of your population. And the
simplest way to do it is to have tax
reforms. And that's exactly what is
being done. Excellent. So it can to some
extent depending on how it is done and
to what extent it is done, it can
significantly definitely uh offset to
some extent at least the impact of Trump
Trump's tariffs. So yeah, it's the
logical step to take and it's being
taken. Excellent.
Pri, thank you very much, sir. I
appreciate that.
geopolitical dub says will the US ever
let Venezuelan oil come into the market?
Well, as long as they Venezuelans are
refuse to become American vas, they will
do everything to prevent Venezuel
Venezuela from selling oil to the rest
of the world. See, take take the example
of Iran. India is to buy oil from Iran.
Then the US came in the way and said
that India can no longer buy oil from
Iran. If you want us not to sanction you
and if you want us to be your friends,
you have to immediately stop buying from
oil from Iran. And because of that,
India stopped buying oil from Iran. And
that caused a lot of friction in the
India Iran relationship. Iran is not an
enemy power of India. India and Iran
should actually be be good friends,
allies, not allies as such, but
partners, right? We don't have any
issues as such, right? But the US came
in the way and that kind of soured the
India U Iran relationship and the
Americans have prevented a lot of
countries in the same way uh from buying
oil from Iran. So Iran's major export
market is China right now, right? And
very other very few other countries are
allowed to buy oil from Iran. So the
Americans can do exactly the same thing
to Venezuela and I'm sure it's being
done right now. And right now Venezuela
is under military pressure from the US.
So yeah, that's the situation. So how
can Venezuela uh end this problem? By be
by becoming an American vasal by having
a regime change and installing a pro- US
puppet in the country and then opening
up their oil sector to US to the US and
the US will benefit and profit from
that. That's what the Americans want.
The Americans want to control the entire
world's flow of energy. You see that's
the thing.
Mansak says should Indians be soft
boycotting American products, movies,
shows till the tariff thing is over or
while only using necessary stuff like
Google etc. I would say let's you know I
I would not recommend any such thing
boycotting and all it first of all it
doesn't work unless the whole country is
united nothing works like that and it's
up to you it's entirely up to you if you
don't like what the Americans are doing
you make your own decisions I will make
no recommendations as such yeah because
the penetration is anyway so deep so it
really doesn't make any difference until
we become technologically a sovereign
nation but uh I would say it's up to
every individual Indian decide what is
best from their perspective. If you feel
that the US is being extremely
oppressive and trying to act like a
colonial power just like the British
again then yeah you can make your
decision.
Aditya thank you very much sir.
Saiti says can Japan rearm
constitutionally? No.
No. And even if they change the
constitution they will not be allowed to
change it. If if some prime minister or
some leader wants to change the
constitution even one word or something
will happen to them and uh the whole
country is under US occupation more than
120 130 permanent US military bases on
Japanese soil um their entire economy is
controlled by the Americans their
foreign policy military policy is
controlled by the Americans they can't
take any m major decision without
consulting the US the American generals
who rule the country Japan can't do
anything
Now
ICMBBS says is it fair to compare the
Roman Republic with the US not the Roman
Republic the Roman Empire see if you
look at so this is not really a
historical question it's a compar
comparison which is valid and and and
fair if you're discussing geopolitics so
so the history of Rome you can say is
roughly you can divide in three parts
one is the Roman kingdom second is the
Roman Republic and third is the Roman
Empire the Roman Roman kingdom was this
small bunch of this small kingdom that
Rome had. Then the Roman Republic is
when Rome becomes powerful and it is run
by a group of people the Senate old guys
who are very powerful and very rich
nobles and that was the Roman Republican
period and that ends essentially with
Julius Caesar and Augustus. Julius
Caesar was the last great figure of the
republican time and then you have
Augustus who becomes the first emperor.
So it is not in not really correct to
compare the Roman Republic with the US.
the Roman Empire. Absolutely. Because
the US is an empire
and it behaves exactly the way the Roman
Empire used to behave from a 21st
century perspective. Not from a 100 AD
perspective, but from a 21st century
perspective, the same patterns apply. So
yes, it is indeed fair to compare the
Roman Empire or any empire for for that
matter with the US because the US is an
empire. It's an autocracy masquerading
as a democracy. It's a two-party system
just one one step above a one party
system and its behavior is entirely
imperial in nature.
Okay. Godliness has some context to
offer to the previous question. Okay. In
the most recent tweet, Prime Minister
Modi termed our relationship with the US
as comprehensive global strategic
partnership. This categorization of the
relationship seems wrong.
This is a diplomatic statement, sir.
It's a diplomatic statement.
In diplomacy, you use nice words
and the words don't matter. You have to
be polite. You have to be courteous. You
have to say the right things. But at the
end of the end of the day, you do what
is right for your country.
We should not take offense with so and
so word was used and that word was not
used or we were not stronger and we did
not give a more robust response. Words
don't matter. Please repeat to yourself
before you go to sleep and first time
first thing in the morning words don't
matter
only actions matter what has what has
India's actions been we have refused to
cave into the US we have refused to acce
the demands to become a vasal to open up
our economy and just do everything they
want those are the actions that we are
taking words don't matter look at the
actions that's all
Daily Dose of Gaming says uh recent
rumors about tariff or tax on it. My
take
let them tax let them put tariff on IT
exports from India to the US. It's going
to hurt their companies because all
their Fortune 500 companies and other
companies their entire tech sector
depends on Indians on on Indian IT
services.
If they want to impose tariffs on that
feel free to do it. It'll hurt our
tariff sector. It will be very damaging
for their fortune 500 companies. I'm
sure they can afford to pay more as
tariffs because who pays tariffs? It's
not India that pays tariffs. It is the
importer who pays tariffs. If I'm a
Fortune 500 company and I'm um I'm
getting services worth let's say a
million dollars in a month from India
and if let's say Trump imposes 50%
tariffs, it means that every time I get
a million dollars worth of services from
India, I have to pay half a million
dollars to the US government. I the
importer the American company the Indian
companies don't pay tariffs
so if they want to if if Trump wants to
do it let him do it it'll hurt the US I
would say go ahead and end the H-1B
system also the visa system I think
India should say we are ending ourselves
the H-1B visa system we require that all
H1B visa holders immediately come back
to India within 7 days time then see
what happens chaos in the US
teen talk the says if the US the US has
military bases in many countries due to
its victory in the second world war. But
today no other country can do that. So
how can one surpass the US military
might? The US in military might. The US
took the fullest advantage of its uh
victory in the second world war. It's
it's uh the hedgemony it established
over Western Europe and they expanded it
by by through the Breton Woods Accord
and uh making the US dollar the global
currency the reserve currency and they
also at that time were in physical
occupation of Japan military occupation
they continued that the Korean wars gave
them another advantage they were able to
occupy South Korea which is still still
under occupation and nations like
Germany Italy etc remain under US
occupation since the second world war
ended and the US over time it expanded
its foot footprint by doing this series
of bilateral acts with lots of countries
which essentially vaselized those
countries with the reward that you know
we will offer you military protection
whenever required and it created NATO it
engineered the EU and that's how it has
been able to expand its global power
projection capabilities economically
militarily and in other ways politically
in so many different ways so today the
situation question is that the US has
more than 700 extr territorial military
bases across the world. Uh no other
country can do that. So how can one
surpass the US and military might?
So you can surpass the US and military
might but it'll be difficult to surpass
them in power projection. You can
develop new technologies
that will let's say your country
develops a new technology military
technology set of technologies that
dwarfs
the capabilities of the US right
so then you become locally super
powerful
and then slowly you can use that might
to expand outwards by creating vasals
around you so it's a process that
happens over time let's say let's say
hypothe Hypothetically, India develops
some superb technology, anti-atter
technology. Let's say we power all our
vehicles through anti matter and all our
military weapons have anti-atter
warheads. Hypothetical completely
science fiction scenario that is more
powerful potentially definitely more
more powerful than nuclear weapons and
it gives you unlimited energy if you can
generate if you can produce enough
antimatter all hypothetical. So with
that kind of power that nobody can
defeat you let's say then India decides
that we will replace the versalization
of Pakistan by the US by making Pakistan
our vasal and we do that do the same
thing with east and east and west
Pakistan and we start expanding our
footprint outwards that way. So it takes
time right it's possible but it will
take time it may take 20 30 40 50 years
but for that one nation will have to
develop technology that is way more
powerful than anything the US has it is
always technology
that is the gamecher
somebody earlier in the previous live
stream today asked me how did the
Vikings become a force suddenly in
Europe they were nowhere technological
innovation
it's always technology
So any country can through technological
innovation surpass the US. It might but
then you will have to work on your power
projection capabilities which is a
different story which also will be much
easier if you have if you have more
white might. So that's how it goes.
Ritik Yadwanchi says as the US is a
continuation of the British Empire why
would they push migrant influx harming
their own land of origin UK and Europe?
Is the west heading towards u civil
unrest or even civil war as tensions
rise? Look, the US is a continuation of
the British Empire. It snatched the
crown from London and replaced and took
it to Washington. And now they look at
the UK as a vasal as a substandard
second rate, third rate world power
which is a vasal of the US. So you can
do whatever you want to your vasal even
if there are your own people. It doesn't
matter if they're their own people,
right? And the US fought the UK for its
independence. So they still have that
that we're going to one up you every
time. We're going to show you who's the
boss. We are the same people. But we are
the boss now. And the UK, you guys, you
stay down. You are our vasals. Everyone
else, all the Anglo countries, Canada,
Australia, everybody, second grade
compared to us. We are the top dog. And
we will show you how things are done.
Right? and if required we'll ruin you.
So that's how it goes. There is no
ethnic loyalty or any such thing.
Is the west uh heading towards civil
unrest or even civil war as tensions
arise? It's possible if you are if your
country if your demographics are being
replaced by invaders that the invasion
is being engineered by by a foreign
power which is Brussels in in in in
Europe. So let's say you are a
hypothetical European nation who is part
of the EU and Brussels is a thousand
kilometers away but Brussels decides
what happens in your country and you do
not elect the people in Brussels. They
don't represent you. They are your
overlords and they are pushing
immigration into your country. It's
possible that tensions will rise and
there could be civil war and people
could revolt possibly.
It's possible Europe may perhaps
potentially hypothetically head in such
a direction. Entirely possible.
Prashant says are royal families
symbolic or they do they impact
geopolitics
which royal families are referring to
the UK's royal family it doesn't really
matter as far as we know right
the UK is a vasal of the US the UK
doesn't matter
which other royal families the European
royal families how do they matter
they're completely insignificant and
immaterial no they don't matter
uh in geopolitics what matters is who
really holds power. Where is the real
center of power in each block, the
western block, the eastern block or or
every country.
So when it comes to the entire western
world which is the US plus NATO plus EU
plus Australia, New Zealand plus now
Japan and South Korea also part of the
western world because they're under
occupation. When it comes to the western
world, there's only one center of power
which is Washington. all your little
royal families and all they don't matter
the real power is in Washington now it
is said that Washington has a deep state
so that is the real power then the deep
state the power that really controls the
US and its economy and all that not the
president the president is just just for
show and in case some people believe
that the deep state is controlled by
some other foreign country then that's
where the power lies I'm just saying
hypothetically so royal families don't
really matter today unfortunately for
them for them in India the royal
families anyway don't matter
Ashish Kuran says how can Japan South
Korea deasalize feels impossible. It's
more or less impossible. They can
devasalize only if the US decides to
release them which the US obviously
won't decide. There's no way they they
they devasalize unless they find some
incredible science fiction technological
breakthrough that can free them of for
an occupation which is extremely
unlikely. So very hard to see this
happening. So I agree with you very hard
feels impossible.
Raj Rahul. Oh, thank you. No question
but thank you so much. Appreciate that.
Shalesh Nyak says, "Can India take
control of the state of Mala?" Well, we
can, but then there'll be a push back,
right? Okay, let's take a look at the
map so that we understand what we
discussing.
We have the naval might to to take
control of it. But the question is if we
do that then what's the consequences of
that?
See this is the straight of Mala. This
here this this passage of water it's
called the Mala straight.
And most of the world's shipping between
east and west passes through the Mala
straight. Whatever Chinese whatever the
whatever energy is imported by China it
passes through the Mala straight. So if
you want to choke China hypothetically
then you need to then you then India can
hypothetically blockade this trait using
its uh using the Indian navy and that
can cause immense problems not just for
China but for the west also and so on uh
because of it'll it'll block the the the
transportation of goods from east from
from Asia to the west and so on. So
it'll cause immense problems. So now
let's say certainly we hypothetically
can blockade it if you want to. We can
send 20 Indian naval warships and a
bunch of submarines to blockade this
place. So nobody can pass through. It
can be done. But then what is the
consequences of that? We have to look
beyond the first order scenario.
If we do that the Chinese will send
their navy to the Malaka strait to face
off against the Indians and to clear the
Indian blockade. Now the Chinese navy is
way more powerful than Indian navy. Do
you know that? Then what do we do? Have
you thought about that? And if we
blockade the state of Malaka, first of
all, will the Americans agree to it?
They will not agree to it. They will say
you are trying to become a big power
now. We will do something about this.
They will send two aircraft carrier
strike groups
to threaten the Indian Navy. Then what
do you do? So look, hypothetically, we
can take some action. Can we let's say
we we blockade the state of Malaka or
let's say we can't take control of it
because it is it is it passes through
Indonesia you can to take control of the
state of Malaka you have to take control
of Indonesia which we don't want to do
so we can't take control of it we can
blockade it but then there's going to be
consequences which will not be nice so
until you become a power such a powerful
nation that nobody can challenge your
blockade there's no point doing it do
you understand
Kingston Crystal says says, "Will we
ever spread our culture and religion
like the west?" See, our culture is not
the kind of culture or religion that
spreads the way the western religions,
Abrahamic religions are spread spread
through the sword. We don't do that. So,
yeah, we will not do it that way and it
doesn't look like we're in in a position
to do it anyway right now.
Anonymous scientist says, "Should India
mediate Russia Ukraine if both agree?" I
think we should. I think we should. show
Trump his place. Putin doesn't Trump uh
doesn't trust Trump. Zalinski is Trump's
puppet, but he's he's also trying to be
as independent as possible.
>> And Trump is not going to able to is not
going to be able to bring forth a
ceasefire unless it is in Putin's
interest to have a ceasefire. And Putin
doesn't need a ceasefire right now. He's
perfectly fine with the way the the war
is going. He's perfectly fine with that.
It is going as per his plans, right? the
slow grinding war. Who is it hurting? Is
it hurting Russia? If if you if you
believe the propaganda coming from the
west, like 700 million Russian soldiers
have died or some nonsense like that or
1 million. How do they get these
numbers? Huh? The war is working exactly
the way Russia wants.
Now, let's say Putin wants a ceasefire,
but he doesn't want to do it through
Trump.
Then maybe India can get involved in
that. So I think in the future if a
ceasefire does happen at some point in
the future maybe it may be India that's
involved rather than the US right it's
possible so if there's the opportunity I
would say that yes India should mediate
in this crisis indeed
Ajinka Pawar says a very interesting
question no one asks this this talks
about the space race right these days
what's currently going on in the space
race. Okay. What's currently going on?
Which are the major space powers in the
world right now? We have the US. Yeah.
We have Russia, we have China, we have
India, we have the EU, which is mainly
France, we have Japan to some extent. Do
have I missed somebody? I guess not. And
in the US, you again have multiple
powers, which is one is NASA or or or
the United Launch Alliance or whatever
it is. The second is Space X. And if you
look at the whole global or scheme of
things, Spac X is the predominant
player in the space race today,
right? They can they launch rockets like
every week. The amount of payload they
can launch in a year is it's it it
dwarfs all the other nations put
together.
So the US is the undisputed leader of
the space race. There's a huge distance
between SpaceX and everybody else. huge
gap.
Um
when it comes to the other nations,
Russia has very robust uh space space
launch capabilities.
So Russia is a powerful player in the
space race. They have powerful rockets,
very reliable rockets
and they don't have a space station.
They don't seem to have very ambitious
plans of uh do the Russians have a plan
to send humans to the moon? They
probably do, but they perhaps may uh do
that in cooperation with China possibly.
China is very ambitious and China's
space launch capabilities are pretty
good, very good, actually excellent.
They've got very good rockets which
hardly fail and the payload capacity is
pretty strong. There's Japan, which is a
pretty good space program, but it's a
Vasal nation, so it doesn't really
matter because it's controlled by the
US. And you have the EU, which again is
controlled by the US. They have the
Arianu rocket system which is a pretty
very very very robust and very reliable
rocket system and then you have ISRO.
Right now I have said this in the past
that the two or three nations that will
lead the world in the space race in
space exploration capabilities will be
the two or three nations that will
decide the future of humankind.
The question is where is India in all
this? We have ISRO. We have the PSLV
which is a tiny little rocket compared
to everybody else. Okay, I'm not trying
to disparage the achievements of our
engineers and scientists. It's a
excellent rocket,
but its payload capacity is minuscule
compared to what other countries have.
Now, can ISRO scientists not develop a
rocket rocket that's 20 times more
powerful? We have the GSLV or the LMV
Mark whatever, which is a augmented
version of the GSLV, which is more
powerful with a higher payload capacity
than the PSLV.
We have that but once again it is
dwarfed by what the Chinese have, the
Russians have and the uh Europeans have
and the Americans have. So our our
scientists, our engineers are capable of
developing in let's say 5 years, 10
years a rocket that's of the same order
of magnitude as the SpaceX most powerful
rockets. We have all the
talent. We have all the knowhow. We have
all the manpower we need. All the brains
we need. But
where's the money? Where's the money?
Where's the ambition?
Let's say I'm an engineer in ISRO. I
want to make the most powerful rocket in
the world. I have the ambition. I that
that hunger inside me, that fire burns
in me. But I am an engineer in ISRO.
I don't control the budget. I don't
decide what happens. I take orders from
my superior and I do what I'm told and
my boss will take orders from somewhere
else.
So the the ambition needs to come at the
political from the political level. The
leadership of India,
right? I would want to see India as the
one of the top two space powers. It's
very important. People don't understand
what's there in rockets. Who needs all
this?
If we had did not even have the PSLV,
GSLV, would we have all the satellites
that we have in space right now? Without
the satellites, we are blind.
Without the satellites, we could not not
have won the operations in war.
We need way more capabilities than what
we have right now. Eventually, the
Americans will start is issuing visas
for the moon and for Mars. Then what
will we do? Then we will be stuck here
and the the the Americans will expand
across the solar system.
our descendants, our children will be
stuck on the planet which by the time
could you know be a very different
planet. So we need
to augment our space flight
capabilities. We need to we have this
gaganyan coming up. I don't know what
the deal is. When is the first flight
happening? There's going to be a couple
of experimental flights and before this
human space flight and so on. It's very
slow tedious snail space progress. Very
disappointing. very disappointing. India
should be one of the top two powers in
space when we have everything we need to
make it happen but there seems to be a
lack of political will and ambition.
That's what I would say.
Nova Spark says someone was saying
months back that Modi and Trump would
dance hand in hand and that's how so I
saw the US India relation. What went
wrong? A failed prediction. First failed
prediction.
Yes. So I had said that there is a high
possibility that India and the US will
dance hand in hand. What did it what did
I mean by that? It meant that India
could become a US vasal
and we have not become US vasal.
I would say I mean my highest regards to
Prime Minister Modi
right to stand up to the US because when
I had said whenever it was November
December whatever that there's a there's
a significant chance that India and the
US will be dancing hand in hand what I
what I meant by that is that India will
there's a high likelihood that India
will become a US vasal
and that's not happened.
So incredible. I'm I'm so proud of the
prime minister and the government for
standing up to the US, right? Um
yeah. So I had said that and it's not
happened and I am super happy it's not
happened. All right.
I'm sure you find it funny. It's okay.
Uh Pawan Shri Hersha says, "Your videos
have been a blessing to me. Thank you so
much. Thank you. Thank you so much. uh
the US is vacating its foreign bases and
is confining to its region. Does this
benefit China?
The US seems to be in a state of
retreat, strategic retreat, right? It is
is it is trying to reimpose the Monroe
Doctrine in the Americas region which is
North and South America. Right now it's
trying to coersse Venezuela through
military threats and so on. And uh
so is the US vacating its foreign bases?
I think it is consolidating its its hold
on its own region.
It is the US is feeling that the Chinese
and the Russians have and perhaps India
also with them will cause a different
will cause a certain kind of shift in
the balance of power in the in the
Eurasia region or in the Asia region. So
maybe now because of this coming shift
we need to consolidate our our
stronghold on what we occupy and our
region our hemisphere of the world let's
say which is the Americas the western
hemisphere and Europe and so on. So they
are kind of taking actions in that
direction. Uh does this benefit China?
Well the US is not withdrawing from
Eurasia from the Asia-Pacific region.
The US is not giving up a single
military base that it has in Japan. It
has more than 120 military bases. It's
not giving up a single one of those.
It's not giving up a single base in
South Korea. It is not giving up the
vasal it has in various countries in the
region, Southeast Asia region, Eastern
Asia region. It's not giving up any of
that. So, it's not really withdrawing.
It's not really vacating its foreign
bases. The French have vacated their
bases in in the Sahel region of Africa.
So the French have well executed a
retreat, a genuine retreat. The French
presence in Africa, military presence in
Africa is over. Now the French have done
that. So you can see overall from a
macro western perspective, the west is
kind of retreating to some extent. Does
this benefit China? Not quite yet.
Because if you look at China, it is
still very much encircled by US bases
and US forces, the three island trains
and whatnot. So it's too early to say
that it it benefits China. The US is not
vacating any of those bases. It's not
giving up any of the island chains. So,
it doesn't really make make any
difference at this point in time to
China. If the US does for some reason in
the future start vacating some of the
bases, maybe some South Korean bases or
Japanese bases, that would be huge
advantage to China if that happens. But
I don't see that happening. So, that's
the situation right now.
Feels strong man says you mentioned
about great men theory in my favorite
most favorite episode of Abijit Chavda
Chingiskar and Alexander great uh yeah
beer biceps okay that episode do you
subscribe to this idea can you elaborate
and please do one more episode we can do
one more episode if you like if if
that's what everyone wants what is this
great man theory
and uh I mean it's it's one of the
theories that seeks to explain how
historical and geopolitical change
happens. Right?
So there are various ways of looking at
the world. One is the Marxist
perspective.
The Marxist perspective doesn't believe
in the great man theory. The Marxist
perspective says it is the workers of
the world. It is the great United
proletariat that that makes the change
in the world. Marxist revolutions and
all that stuff. Uh and and individuals
don't matter. That's the Marxist
perspective. But the great man theory
says that all major change in world
history has happened through the actions
of a small number of great men.
Major change, not small changes here and
there, little minor changes, major
changes.
For example, Alexander is said by the
west to have changed the course of
history of the world. Right? One man and
his conquests, he destroyed Persia. He
destroyed Persia. He destroyed the
greatness that Persia had. The Aminate
dynasty was ended by Alexander and
Persia was reduced to a shell of what it
used to be. All its treasures were
plundered by Alexander. All the gold and
silver was taken and melted away. All
the books and libraries were destroyed
and burned. Nothing was left. So yeah,
huge change. And so Alexander is is one
of the great men that they talk about.
There are other great men. Julius
Caesar. No question about the fact that
Julius Caesar single-handedly changed
the course of history in Europe, right?
He single-handedly was the cause of the
end of the Roman Republic and the
beginning of the imperial period of
Rome. It would not have happened without
the conquests that he did. He conquered
Gaul, which is today's France. He
conquered Iberia, which is today's
Spain. He conquered he he was the first
Roman to conquer parts of of Britain. He
was not content with that. He went and
conquered Greece. Then he went and
conquered Egypt and so much more. So one
man had such a huge impact on creating
this whole empire, right? For setting up
the structure that would become the
Roman Empire. Then you have Chingis
Khan. One man single-handedly changed
the course of history in in Asia, right?
And uh what he did still has
repercussions today. And so many
examples even in Indian history. Chandra
Gupta Maria Ashok
various Gupta emperors
the Cholas Rajendra Rajan Rajendra Chola
they changed the course of world history
so if you look at the patterns you will
see it's always some then there's
Napoleon there is in Turkey Mustafa
Kimal Ataturk in in Russia there's
Stalin
and and so on so if you look at history
it's it's you will see there are these
individuals that that come up at various
points in
And through the sheer force of their
personality and efforts and their
achievements and their deeds, they take
the the world by the th by the scruff of
its neck and change the course of
history.
Um so yeah there there is a significant
amount of truth the way I see it to the
great man theory.
U so yeah I I say I would say that to
some extent I do subscribe to this idea.
Yeah it's not and and who is a great
man? A great man is typically a product
of the culture that he grew up in. So
culture also obviously makes a
difference. Uh when it comes to India
Chhatraat Shivaji Maharaj, great example
of a great man who changed the course of
history. He laid the foundations for
what would become the Marata Empire
which destroyed the Turkish stronghold
over India. Right? So one man laid the
foundation for what would become the
Marata Empire. So you have this happen
over and over again in history and that
is something that's undeniable. Of
course there are other perspectives.
Um but yeah overall I would say that to
to a significant extent it's true.
Arun says
no hate but provin moan is debunked by
Indian rationalist and historians is
literally saying 200 years carbon dating
as 200 2,000 years supporting him blah
blah blah. So we are discussing
geopolitics here.
We are discussing geopolitics here. It's
okay. You don't have to believe in
Pravin Mahan or anybody else. You don't
have to believe in me also. It's okay.
>> I am not a rationalist by the way. I'm
not a rationalist. I'm a realist.
Rationalism is idiocy. The Indian
rationalists are are a bunch of
crackpots. Many of them. Not all. I'm
sure there are brilliant words among
them. But this whole rationalism
business is all about essentially being
anti-vilivilization and anti-ulture and
I'm not one of these Indian rationalists
right it's up to you sir anyway back to
geopolitics let's not please see I'll
not take any further questions that's
outside of geopolitics I agree sir no
hate and I appreciate that please feel
free to believe whatever you believe
it's entirely up to you I will not
dispute your right to believe whatever
you like
some guy on the says, "What are the
geopolitical impacts of an Islamic US,
Europe, Japan as the illegal immigration
to these countries is rising unchecked?"
Um, Islamic US is is a is a far-fetched
scenario as of today,
right? What's the Islamic population
percentage of the US? 1% 2% 3%. I'm sure
it's less than 3%. Shall we fact check
that? What's the what's the Islamic
Let's Let's take some countries as an
example. Okay. Uh percentage of US
Muslim population. Let's see what's it
say
1.34%. Okay. 1.34%. So as you can see
it's very low. UK what 6% that is 6 to
6.5%. Huge. France let's say France.
France must be 10% plus
percentage bro. 10%. Yeah, about 10% in
2023 2019 2020 that's France you asked
about okay Europe what about Germany
let's see
Germany was 6 7% 10% yeah there you have
it 6.1 to 6.7% Japan must be very low
right now but it's rising because the
Americans are put pushing in certain
flavors of immigrants into Japan now uh
less than 1% I'm sure 0.2 to to 0.3% but
it may it is increasing now. Yeah. Uh so
I think when it comes to Europe it's
possible that Europe could become
Islamic in in a few decades entirely
possible. US I would say at this point
in time it's very very highly unlikely.
Japan uh right now it's a very small
population but uh if the Americans
decide that we'll send in a few million
Bangladeshes and a few million
Pakistanis then it may change very
significantly very fast. an Islamic
Japan. Well, if if that happens, what's
the geopolitical impact of that? Well,
you could have the spread of Islam there
and that comes with geopolitical uh um
consequences. Obviously, Islamic Europe.
Uh what could be the consequences of
that? Well, it'll be a different culture
and it will have a different approach to
geopolitics.
The kind of approach various caliphate
and all have had in the past which is a
very robust geopolitical approach. an
approach of hedgemony and conquest and
that sort of thing that could happen
right uh so that's all down in the
future maybe if it happens in Europe it
could happen in the next 30 40 years
perhaps that it becomes a significant uh
Islamic population and then Europe's
entire nature personality everything
will change right uh it could be like
the days when Spain was an Islamic
country when the Moors the North African
Muslims
used to rule Spain. So Spain was at that
time an expansionist. The Moish Spain
was an expansionist power which wanted
to destroy France, subjugate France and
and Islamize France as well and then do
the rest of the and continue for the
rest of Europe. Right? What about
Ottoman Turkey? They also wanted to do
the same thing from the east. Go
westwards and colonize the whole of
Europe and Islamize Europe. So the same
thing could happen if certain portions
of Europe become Islamic officially or
whatever it is right. So that sort of
thing could happen.
Himmanu says why exactly is the dollar
powerful? Is it just the sheer power of
the US that backs it? How does it work?
Thank you. Okay.
Currency is is very powerful. I'll tell
you why.
So how did this happen? First of all, it
it all happened in 1944, 1945. The
Bretonwoods agreement. The US was very
clear that it's going to now win the
Second World War. Germany is on the way
out. Japan will be defeated. We have the
Manhattan project going. So then a bunch
of countries came together and accepted
the American demand that the US dollar
should be become the world's reserve
currency, which means that whenever you
do transactions internationally, you do
it in the US dollar. And the US dollar
was backed with gold at the time. By 71
the gold backing was removed by Nixon
and it was that it then became the petro
dollar because the US controlled the
global supply of petroleum because it
controlled the Middle East region, Saudi
Arabia, all the major oil producing
countries. Uh so so there and eventually
the US dollar is not no longer even
dependent on oil. Now it's just a paper
currency with no intrinsic value of its
own but it is still the reserve currency
because of US military might.
the US. If any country decides to stop
using the dollar, there's going to be
tremendous
consequences, very bad consequences for
that country. The US will sanction the
country. It may launch a military
invasion of the country or it may
disconnect the country from the global
financial order. For example, what they
did to Russia, they disconnected Russia
from Swift. They froze all the Russian
bank accounts. Whatever money the
Russians had in various countries,
various bank accounts was frozen,
stolen, whatever, that's what they will
do to you. So then if the whole world is
trading in the dollar but you are no
longer able to do it. It means you are
cut off financially in economically from
the rest of the rest of the world. You
can't trade because for trade you need
the common accepted currency. Right? So
the Americans have created the situation
where the only common accepted currency
globally internationally is the US
dollar. Now the thing things now the
situation is changing. The Russians and
the Japanese the Russians and the the
Chinese they have a ruble yuan trade.
India Russia we have a rupee rubal
trade. So there are countries that are
now diversifying beyond the US dollar.
Then the Americans also created a proxy
currency which was the euro which also
is a currency they control right. So
they gave the the world an illusion of
options but it was essentially the same
thing because the euro is essentially
the Deutsch mark. It's a rebranded
Deutsch mark and the Deutsch Bundus Bank
is controlled by the US which has now
become the European bank or whatever it
is right. So at the end of the day why
is the dollar so powerful? Because the
US is the sole superpower. It's the one
hgemon that can intervene anywhere in
the world at 60 minutes notice
militarily.
And that's what keeps the dollar the
world's reserve currency because
everyone is afraid,
right? If they stop using the dollar,
they're going to smash us. That's why
the sheer power, military power of the
US backs the US dollar. There's no other
reason for the world to use the dollar.
It has no intrinsic value anymore. It's
just a piece of paper. They print
dollars whenever they feel like and that
causes problems globally. But that's
what it is. It is it is the sheer
military might of the US that guarantees
that enforces the status that the US
dollar has as the world's reserve
currency.
Satellite says name all Indian vasals.
Which Indian vasals?
We are not a vasal nation.
We are one of the five sovereign nations
in the world. Which are the five
sovereign nations? The US, Russia,
China, India, and Israel.
We aren't vasals. If you are talking
about some historical issue, well, we're
not discussing issu history right now.
Pranayumar says Pakistan and Bangladesh
made a choice. Do we destroy them?
We can obviously destroy them but what
will be the consequences?
Today Pakistan is under US protection.
Do you understand that Bangladesh is
also under US protection? Both East
Pakistan and West Pakistan are today US
assets, US vasals. And what is the deal
in vasalhood? Let's say I am a small
power and I am the vasal of my great
emperor the the imperial power. What is
the deal in vasalhood? It means I will
do everything it takes
to serve his interests which can include
sometimes selling off some parts of my
country if required or selling off my
people. So I will victimize my people to
ensure that the emperor is happy. But in
exchange for that whenever I am under
threat the emperor will come and save me
because I am useful to him. So you think
we can just like that just destroy
Pakistan and Bangladesh because we feel
like you think there'll be no
consequences sir. That's that's the
point. You have to think deeper. My dear
friends, my dear friends please
understand this. When you do an analysis
of a geopolitical situation or a
business situation or a life problem,
please go beyond the surface level.
Look at the surface level. What look
what things look like on the surface,
but then take the time, put in the
effort to go deeper, one level deeper,
second level deeper, third level deeper.
Okay, Pakistan enemy, very bad guy. But
who are Pakistan's
allies.
Ask yourself this question,
who is supporting Pakistan and for what
reason are they supporting Pakistan?
And then if you establish what that
relationship is and why this great power
is supporting Pakistan, then ask
yourself, if you harm Pakistan, it will
harm the great power's interest because
Pakistan is a valuable asset. Then will
that great power not do something to
stop it? Think about it.
Wooden Armor PK says, "How is it that
countries like Thailand, Malaysia became
first world so easily despite being much
weaker economically and militarily while
India can't?
When you are a smaller nation, it's way
easier to implement reforms and make
changes.
Okay, it also depends on the kind of
government you have.
So let's say
Take the example of Singapore for
example. Okay, we're talking about the
same region in our neighborhood east of
India, Southeast Asia.
In the Thailand Malaysia neighborhood,
you have Singapore also.
In the 1950s,
Singapore was a povertyridden third
world country.
Small little place, small country like a
city state almost completely objective,
objectly povertyridden.
In 20 years, it became a first world
country because of what factors?
First of all, it had the right
leadership. It had Lee Kuan Yu as the
leader, as the benevolent dictator.
It had the right form of government, a
dictatorship, which means that whatever
the dictator decides will be done
quickly. There'll be no stupid
opposition to come and say no, we should
not do this, we should not do that.
Human rights blah blah environment blah
blah blah.
The entire system of the government was
aligned with Leewanu. The judiciary,
the executive, the military, the police,
the etc etc etc etc. Businesses,
everybody did what they were told. So
things happened fast, right? And he was
a person with a vision. He may have been
a dictator, but he was a benevolent
dictator.
He was an ironfisted dictator, but his
his his vision was that of a prosperous
Singapore and a happy Singapore. And he
enforced iron discipline. So that's how
in just one generation, just 20 years,
Singapore went from a third world
hellhole to a first world country.
Right? Great example Singapore. Now
Thailand, Malaysia are much larger than
Singapore. But compared to India, they
are much smaller.
And if you look at the system of
government, it is different from the
system of government in India.
Of course, if you look at it
superficially, you will say, "No, but
they also have parliament. They also
have this." Please go beyond surface
level analysis and you will see that the
reality is actually different. The truth
is not always what you see at the
surface level.
Right.
Um
so that's why
smaller countries can change faster.
Smaller countries can reform faster and
if you can deal with issues like
corruption and eradicate corruption like
Singapore did, well things become so
much simpler if the what is the meaning
of the word corruption in in the modern
context? What does corruption mean? Huh?
Do you know what corruption means? Can
you can you define in one sentence what
corruption means?
What is the definition? What what is
what is it? What do you mean when you
say that the system is corrupt?
What does it mean when you say the
system is corrupt or or system is
government system or whatever?
When you say it is corrupt, what does it
mean? It means that its status its
stated function and purpose is X but
actually it does not do X. It does Y.
Its stated function and purpose is to
serve the people in the nation. But its
actual what it actually does it serves
somebody else. It serves a small number
of people from who are insiders while
pretending while claiming that we are
working for the nation. That's the
definition of corruption. When a system
does not do what it's supposed to do but
does something else which is detrimental
to the to the cause it's supposed to
serve. That's the meaning of corruption.
So Singapore solved the problem of
corruption. Other countries they will be
dealing with it in their own way. So
when you have a gigantic country, India
is gigantic, you may not realize how
gigantic it is. Then and especially when
you are a democracy, a real chaotic
democracy, then any small even the
smallest change faces so much opposition
and resistance and that's why every
little thing takes so long.
Every small little action takes long.
Even if it's good, you have to roll back
sometimes. No, because these people are
protesting. So, we have to roll back the
reforms and apologize. Sorry.
That's what happens in a democracy. So,
you understand
they are smaller than India. All these
nations, the Asian tigers for example,
smaller than India, militarily and
economically much, let's say, weaker
than India. But they were able to do
things, get things done. Look at
Vietnam.
small nation. It's got like roughly
twice the GDP per capita than India.
Look at the streets. Look at the the the
civic sense and all.
Look at how things are far better than
India. Such a nice much nicer place to
live in.
The quality of life is so much better.
It's a communist country officially.
H why is it different? So there are so
many factors that go into this you see.
And if you have a dictatorship like a
communist country, you can get things
done so much better and so much faster.
You can get reforms done faster.
So that's the deal. India has all these
internal problems
that prevent India from reforming and
prevent India from doing anything fast.
And that's why India remains mired in
the third world problems.
Right? This is by design. The system was
designed to be like this from the very
beginning
essentially since 194 from before 1947
it was designed like this you see that's
the deal
Ashish Karan says India alerting
Pakistan over incoming floods thoughts
very kind of us to do that very nice and
I wish our Pakistani
friends all the best I hope the floods
don't hurt you too
Manuk says, "In our democracy, radical
changes for the greater good fail as
people vote out governments at the
slightest discomfort. Is
authoritarianism the only way forward
for India?"
Look, why is the US such a great
country? Now people consider China to be
a great country as well. What do the two
nations have in common? Why is Russia
again becoming a great country? What do
the three countries have in common? the
US, China, and Russia. Authoritarianism.
The US masquerades as a democracy, but
it's an authoritarian regime. It's a
police state. You take one step out of
line, the cops will shoot you there.
Everybody is strictly under control. Of
course, some people these days are
allowed to do things. You will always
some some very smart, intelligent,
well-informed people will say, "No, but
it is not like that. So and so people do
all kinds of stuff in the US and the
cops don't take any action. Please
understand that politics is a different
story and there are political reasons
for that. But overall in the US you
don't take a step out of line. The cops
will shoot you right. It's an
authoritarian country rigidly
authoritarian country. China same thing.
Russia well what do you think is Shri
Putin
um well you could say many people call
him a dictator. Well, if he is one, he's
a benevolent dictator for his country,
right? So, if you have a democracy where
everything has to be done, every
decision has to be first arrived at by
consensus and then you have to take it
to a vote and then you have to see
whether other some special interest
groups have a problem with that, who
will go to some other authority who will
come and step in your way and there'll
be a 17-year delay. If that's the kind
of thing that is going to continue in
India, nothing will change. And of
course if the government stops giving
freebies to so and so category of people
and then they will vote the government
out then once again the country will
always come back to the lowest form of
governance the the most mediocre level
of governance.
So if India wants to be great well then
all you have to ask yourself is this
India used to be great. The past
thousand years we have not been great.
We have had flashes of greatness. The
Barata Empire was was a great empire
right? We were great once again during
the Marata Marata period and before the
Turk occup invasions and occupation of
India we've had great we've reached
great heights at various times the Moria
Empire the Gupta Empire the Kushan
Empire great glorious periods of our of
our history
what worked at that time and what what
was different from what we have today
authoritarianism
right but not evil authoritarianism
Benevolent authoritarianism, dharmic
authoritarianism.
Rajat Chhat Chhati says, "Well, you're
very welcome. First of all, sir, is the
Indian Navy being a bluewater navy? Does
it make any difference to Chinese Navy
on geopolitical power projection?" See
the Indian Navy is indeed a bluewater
navy? What what do we mean by a
bluewater navy? See there are some
navies okay in some countries every
country has some form of navy but many
countries have a navy that is
essentially just a coast guard
it doesn't go into the deep oceans it it
stays clo close close to the coast it
just guards and patrols the coastline
maybe five boats with some machine guns
and some cannons or whatever that's it
so that's not a blue water navy that's a
brownwater navy it's a coastal navy it's
it's a glorified coast guard
But when you have a nation, when you
have a navy that has destroyers, that
has frigots, that has aircraft carriers,
that has submarines
that can go thousands of kilometers on a
mission, well, that's a blue water navy,
right? So, India does have a blue water
navy. Now, does it make any difference
to the Chinese navy?
Okay, let's uh for this, we will have to
look we have to consult the map. So, the
Indian Navy is indeed a blue water navy.
Uh does the Indian Navy have a complete
dominance over the Indian Ocean region?
Not really.
So we don't have the numbers to totally
dominate the entire region that we claim
to be ours, the Indian Ocean region. Um
for that you would need hundreds of
warships. We don't have that number, but
we have sufficient numbers to be very
powerful and very deadly
closer to the coast. But we certainly
can can send warships on very long
missions if required. So, we are a
bluewater navy, but the numbers aren't
that great. And at the end of the day,
you to ask yourself, what is the true
measure of the power of a navy? Before I
go to the map, what's the real measure
of the power of navy? How powerful is
navy X compared to navy Y? How do you
decide how powerful X is versus Y? Do we
decide on the basis of how many how many
ships you have? X has 20 ships, but Y
has 30 ships, so Y is more powerful. No,
not necessarily. X for X who only has 20
ships. Maybe each ship can carry 100
missiles. But Y who has 30 ships, each
ships, each ship can carry only 10 20
missiles. So Y has 30 ships but 60
missiles deployed.
And X has 20 ships but 200 missiles
deployed.
Can you see the difference in power?
Those 20 ships will overwhelm those 30
ships. So the only measure of a navy's
power, of its deadliness, is how many
missiles can you deploy on any given day
in total at sea. And the Chinese Navy
has a vast advantage over India. Okay,
let's not kid ourselves. And the Chinese
Navy has vastly more ships than India.
It dwarfs the Indian Navy. It is now
numerically the largest navy in the
world, the Chinese Navy. But why was I
bringing out the map? It's because the
Chinese Navy is stuck
inside the island trains. The first
island chain which is Japan, Taiwan, all
of that. The second island chain is the
the Philippines and all you have the the
Guam and all of that. So there are three
island chains that the Chinese are
constrained by and they face the all the
US bases in Japan and South Korea which
means that a significant portion of the
Chinese navy has to be deployed in the
Yellow Sea in the East China Sea. Now
they have created a whole new fraka in
the South China Sea. So a lot of the
navy has to be stationed in the in the
South China Sea as well. So because of
that they are not able to to to allocate
significant naval resources for the
Indian Ocean region the
you know this region over here the
Kolinga saga and the sea of Sarashtra
they are not able to do that they would
love to but all of the resources are
tied up over here
but if let's say hypothetically India
decides to blockade the state of Malika
the Chinese will send a whole armada of
warships that will outnumber and
outmatch to the Indian Navy at this
point in time. Okay. So being a blue
water navy is wonderful, great, all that
and India can take on all challenges,
that's true.
But if it's a face down between the
Indian and Chinese navies with full
strength, no chance. So that's why I
keep saying India needs to augment its
naval might. We need to enhance our
distributed lethality, not concentrate
our lethality on a few few gigantic
warships. We need to have a large number
of small to medium warships. Some with
long legs, some with short legs. Some of
them can be big warships with very long
legs. But we need to have a distributed
set of assets of different kinds. We
need to really really have a large
number of submarines and we need to
ensure that we can deploy several
thousand missiles at sea on any given
day at any given point in time. That's
what needs to happen.
Ashish Karan says Kraistmas land bridge
project. What are my thoughts? Well,
they've been talking about that for a
very long time. See what is the Yeah,
let's talk about that. Sure, why not?
Good. Good. Interesting topic. The
Kraistmas, right? So, the Chinese are
worried about the straight of Mala
because yeah, it's it's a choke point
that can be choked off. Even the Indians
can choke it off and it'll be difficult
for the Chinese to do something about
it. The Chinese obviously has the naval
might, but when you have a place like
this, such a narrow straight, even
your naval might may not be very
effective. Even if you have a larger and
more powerful navy, depending on how the
other navy is positioned and what
strategies it uses in conjunction with
the air force and whatnot. So the state
of Malaka is kind of the Achilles heel
for China. So the Chinese have proposed
on many occasions to create a a canal
through Thailand. Uh where exactly is
cry? I don't remember where it is. But
you know, imagine this. See this long
Thai peninsula that eventually becomes
Malaysia. See if you see here this is
Thailand as you can see. Now this all
this territory on the eastern side is
Thailand. Thailand. Thailand right?
Thailand. Suratani is here. Nakoni
Tamarat. Sonla, Patani all the way up to
here it is Thailand and south of that
you have Malaysia. So this is a pretty
narrow strip of land. So what if you
just build a canal like the Suez canal
to this let's say let's say
hypothetically here what's the distance
it's about 70 80 km it's definitely
feasible feasible from an engineering
perspective. So that's the that's the
idea that's been around for quite some
time, many decades actually, that the
Chinese will uh finance this project and
it will help China gain an alternative
to the state of Malaa.
Interesting proposal. Will the Thai
government agree to that? I'm not sure
about that. Uh but even if it is done,
does it really give China an alternative
to the state of Malaa? I mean if the
Indian navy can blockade the straight of
Malaa we can also blockade a canal here
it's not that difficult right so it
doesn't really solve the problem and
that's the re the real issue with this
land bridge it's not just about uh
having an extra passage it's about
bypassing a choke point but by bypassing
a choke point you're creating a new
choke point here so see you see the
issue there that's the problem
okay says why did the British Empire in
the 19th century allow the US to grow to
eventually replace it in the 1920s. Why
didn't they the US like the US
did to Japan and now to India? This may
sound like a historical question but
it's very relevant to geopolitics. So
let's take it. This is a geopolitical
question. This is about geostrategy of
that time which is not that long ago.
See the British Empire in the 19th
century it had a global quasi global
empire. The sun never set on the British
Empire and so on. So why didn't they
the US?
It's a it's a valid question to ask. Why
didn't the British take steps to to
the US? The US that fought the
British, defeated the British and freed
this entire continent. Why didn't the
British then take steps to the
US? Because they would possibly
eventually become a gigantic empire
themselves, right? The US, which has now
happened. So why didn't the British take
any steps to the US?
To answer the question, you to ask
yourself this qu this question.
Were the British in any position to
the US? Did the British at the
time, despite their global empire, have
power projection capabilities in North
America?
Do you know how large North America is?
Let's go to the map. Okay, the British
Empire was all across the world. you
know, Egypt and the Gulf region, India,
Burma,
Malaysia,
Singapore, Australia, New Zealand, and
and so much more, right? So much more.
So much more. So, it essentially never
saw sunset.
But the United States had this enormous
territory,
unlimited territory, unlimited natural
resources.
And they had they had the beginnings of
a pretty strong
military. They could certainly defend
themselves. And the British from here
from from here, they would have to cross
the Atlantic.
And to the US, they would have
to mount an invasion of the US.
Did they have the resources, the means,
the military might to mount an invasion
of the US with its unlimited land and
unlimited resources? Impossible.
Impossible. Even if they wanted to
the US, they would not have
succeeded. When the Americans as they
become more powerful, they impose the
Monroe Doctrine that no European power
will be will be allowed to meddle in the
political affairs of either North
America or South America. Absolutely
nobody. And and soon they started
enforcing that with their military
might. Initially the British actually
helped them. That's a whole different
story. We'll not go into that. So that
was the deal. So eventually the British
said that okay, they are our cousins.
They are our own people. but now they're
a different country and let's have
beneficial mutually beneficial relations
with them and they they could see that
there's no way they can defeat them.
There's no way they can them.
How do you someone? If you want
to a country, you blockade the
country, right? You deprive it of
resources. You deprive it of resources
and you deprive it of communication with
other countries. But the US was so
gigantic. What will you deprive the US
of? It has everything you need. It needs
an otarchy.
Could not work. Could not ever work. And
that's the great advantage the US has.
It is safeguarded by two oceans on two
sides, the the Atlantic Ocean and the
Pacific Ocean. It's almost impossible
conceivably for anyone to invade the US.
Impossible. That's the great advantage
they have. So it was not possible for
the British to do it even if they wanted
to.
And they did not have the kind of power
projection capabilities that the US has
today. So once again,
Mr. independent variable says why didn't
we prepare a backup in case the US left
us
backup of what kind? We have
alternatives, right? We have Russia. We
are talking to China again. So we have,
you could say options.
We have options. We are not dependent on
the US.
Of course, we are technologically
dependent on the US. We are
technologically
pretty dependent on the US in a variety
of ways. So that needs to be done. That
needs to be looked into. But overall, we
are not dependent on the US. We have
alternatives. We have excellent
relations with Russia. We have excellent
relations with France. We have excellent
relations with various Gulf nations. We
are again possibly going to have
decentish relations with China depending
on how things go. So we have we are
working on alternatives. It's not like
we have no backup. Okay. Understand that
please.
Okay. Koshal Talapadi says
what do you make Pentagon paper of US
retreating to western hemisphere come up
with G2 kind of arrangement with China.
Another question about a US retreat. So
look, the US is not militarily
retreating from Eurasia or from uh
Eastern Asia. In Eurasia, they have the
whole NATO framework which is set up
over there and they're going to maintain
their power projection and uh occupation
capabilities in Europe. The same goes to
South Korea, North Korea, uh South Korea
and Japan. But the US is now beginning
to to reinforce its position in in the
Americas. So they want to ensure so the
the steps they want to take is possibly
do a regime change in in Venezuela so
that they can control all the oil
reserves of Venez Venezuela. Venezuela
is is the one nation in the region in
South America that has refused to
vasalize itself to the US. So the
Americans may do something about that
and they want to
essentially entrench their security
position and posture in the Americas
because they are now concerned concerned
that China and Russia could possibly
expand in the future. So let's let's
first of all u secure our home base and
home territories and the territories we
control closer to home. So I think the
US is concerned. The world is changing.
The US is no longer the dominant power.
It was 20 years ago. They had this
uniolar moment where nobody could could
challenge them. But because they aided
and abided China and helped China rise,
that's why we they are in the situation
today. So the world is different today.
The world is more bipolar or multipolar
than it was the the than the kind of
uniolar world you had around 19 in the
1990s and 2000s. Very different. So the
US is concerned but it's not giving up
its uh global hedgemony and power
resistation capabilities anytime soon.
But yes uh G2 you mentioned right the US
would love a G2 arrangement. See they
would the Americans would way prefer
would prefer way much a lot more a
bipolar world than a multipolar world. A
multipolar world is complicated. The
Abrahamic mindset only understands
binarity the binary thing right? Good
versus bad black versus white. uh that
sort of thing. So they would like a
binary world in which one part of the
world hopefully the larger part of the
world is ruled by the US. So which is
the US and its vasals and the other part
will be China, Russia and whoever is
with them. So they want a G2 situation
where the US and China will agree that
now we are the only two enemies. You
have your your minions, I have my
minions and that's the game we play like
the US and the USSR. They prefer that.
But if you have like four different
major powers that's complicated and they
don't like that they don't want it. So
they would want actually
it to be a G2 kind of world bipolar
world and for that they want to make
India
their vasal so that so that India can
become part of the
part of their pole instead of being an
independent player. So that's why they
are going after India right now. Yeah.
So that makes sense. See it makes sense
from this G2 perspective.
Mm says the Japanese prime minister has
resigned. Arm twist by the US
arm twist by US trade deal India.
The Japanese prime minister the news has
come out has resigned. And why has he
resigned? He has resigned because of the
humiliating trade agreement trade deal
that Japan was made to accept by the US.
So the US will impose 15% tariffs on
Japan and Japan will impose lower
tariffs on US goods. So there itself you
have you don't have reciprocity. The US
has the dominant hand and Japan is
forced to swallow extra extra tariffs.
But that's not enough. That isn't
enough. That's not the whole that's not
the entirety of the deal. Beyond that,
Japan has been forced to agree to invest
$550
billion in the US. Japanese money, $550
billion will be invested in the invested
in the US, but not where Japan wants to
invest it. Trump will tell Japan
how to invest the money and where to
invest the money in what way. So, it
means that the money will be controlled
by the US. It means that the Americans
are going into Japan. They are putting
their hands into Japan's pocket, taking
out $550 billion, and they will take it
and use it whichever way they want.
Outright colonial behavior.
Right? So, essentially, they're taking
this. They're taking Japan's money and
they will use whichever way they want.
That's a great trade deal. It's a
pleasure working for Donald Trump. See
how easy things are. We can make anyone
do whatever whatever we want. India bad
boy that sort of thing. So this is
humiliating for Japan.
This deal is an is an utter humiliation
for Japan. And that's why the prime
minister of Japan has resigned. But does
it make any difference? No. The deal
will continue. So some new person will
come up as the prime minister of Japan
and that person will have to be bear the
humiliation and take it forward and and
operationalize the humiliation.
That's the deal. And the US wants to do
exactly the same to India maybe worse
because in India is not a US facile
right now. So the first step is that
they will say open up your market
entirely.
You will impose 0% tariffs on on
American goods and services. Open up
your market entirely. Then if you agree
to that we will maybe impose 15% tariffs
on your goods to the US only 15% instead
of 50 or 500. Right? So you take that
humiliation once you do that once India
let's say hypothetically opens up the
market it will destroy all the Indian
economies Indian companies the Indian
manufacturing sector because all the
American goods will flow in and our
manufacturers will be out of business
then when India is fully economically
dependent they will say now we want
military bases in India that will be the
next step so then slowly they will put
up military bases in India which would
be controlled by the US which will have
American soldiers and personnel. Indians
will be not allowed and that's the
beginning of the occupation of India
just like Japan was occupied. That's the
deal. Colonial
strategy, colonial desires and it's not
going to happen. So that's why they're
so unhappy.
V says China banned US apps creating a
gap. Shouldn't we do it too to achieve
tech sovereignty as we don't have
resources like the US to innovate and
replace them?
And I'm not sure it will work that way.
See, we can ban Chinese apps, but US
apps if we ban them, then then what will
happen?
How will Indians communicate with each
other?
We are used to communicating with each
other any time of the day or night,
right? Indians can communicate with each
other with each with themselves.
Whether you are in Shillong, if whether
you are in Thirucharapali, whether you
are in Lei, whether you are in in Port
Blair in the Andermans, we communicate
with with each other on social media and
various apps in real time. All of this
is American apps. You ban that the whole
country is suddenly disconnected. What
do you do then? You to first create
something to replace that. We need to
have our own apps which are good enough
to be to to be able to replace US apps.
not substandard apps that nobody likes
to use. Right? So there has to be a
process a series of steps to reach that
the desired end goal. India needs to
start creating its own platforms and
apps and these platforms and apps have
to be worldclass not substandard.
Right? So that's what needs needs to
happen. Whether we have resources or not
we have enough money. Come on. We have
enough money to create our own platforms
and whatnot. You just need the will to
do that.
Teen Talks Dharma said says Putin and
Shiv were talking about immortality by
replacing their organs again and again.
Is it possible by today's medical
standards?
Interesting perspective. Okay, I was not
aware of this.
Let's say a person wants to be immortal.
But but is it possible?
See, after a certain age, organs fail,
right?
By the time you're 90 or if you reach
100, your organs are going to be in a
very bad shape and at at some point in
time something will fail and you're
done. That's it. End of story. But what
if you just replace all the organs?
That's a science fiction concept.
There's a science fiction novel
called The Gift from Earth by Larry Nan
in which this sort of concept is
discussed. Anyway, I'll not go into
science fiction right now. Let's say you
have a person who wants to keep on
living forever but their organs are
failing. The the person in the in the '
90s. So what if
you replace the heart, you replace the
lungs, you replace the liver, the
kidneys,
will that person live longer? Presumably
that person could live longer. Now their
eyesight is failing. You replace the
corneas or whatever, suddenly you have
better eyes. But what if there is
macular degeneration? Can you replace
the retina? You can't. So eyesight may
deteriorate.
Then
there's the question of the nervous
system.
Well, which is the major component of
the nervous system? It's the brain.
Can you replace the brain? The brain
also would deteriorate, right? Why is it
that people when they're in the 70s,
80s, 90s, they they become mentally less
functional than they were in the 20s,
30s, 40s, 50s? Why is that? Even 60s?
because the the brain tissue itself
deteriorates,
right? It's it's a very rare case where
you have a 90-year-old who's as sharp as
he or she was in their 50s or 40s. Very
very rare.
Generally, people become slower.
So you can
potentially possibly ensure
that you live longer than usual by
replacing all the major important organs
in lungs, the liver, the heart, the
kidneys, whatever else, maybe even the
corneas. But what do you do about this?
The brain. The brain will deteriorate.
That's the real problem. So up to a
certain extent, you can keep the body
alive. Maybe 120 years, maybe who knows,
maybe, possibly longer, possibly if we
take this weird extreme measures of
replacing all the major organs, but then
you will have to give a cocktail of
anti- anti- uh those suppressant drugs
that suppress the immune system, right?
Because your body will try to reject the
the foreign transplanted organs because
they came from a different body and it's
a foreign organism in your body. Now,
that's how the immune system sees that.
So, you have to give imunosuppressent
drugs for the rest of the life. And when
you're in in in your advanced age and
you're given and you're taking
imunosuppressent drugs, it can cause
infections and things which you and and
you can't replace the immune system,
right? So there are all these
complications very interesting to a
certain extent you can you can do it but
the main question is what about the
brain? Can't replace the brain.
Arun says I believe the first enemy we
have is self self-loathing Indians. They
always see the worst in India. They say
yeah that capital even though it's one
of the lowest in the world per capita
when India overtook Japan economy per
capita matters. Yeah. And how do we
solve this problem? Why are so many
Indians self-loathing?
Are they bad people?
I promise you most Indians are nice
people. You meet them face to face,
person to person, they'll be nice
people. They'll treat you well. They'll
be polite, courteous, all of that. But
they will have this mindset of
inferiority
and they'll hate everything about Indian
culture. They will not most of them will
not be bad bad persons. So why do they
have this mindset? Ask yourself this.
It's because our system brainwashes this
into people. The education system
creates self-loathing people.
Your your teachers, your education
system, I'm not saying all your teachers
are bad. Some are gems.
Sometimes you meet really good teachers
but overall the average standard is very
low
and that's why when you are taught this
nonsense over and over again from the
time you were 3 years old it will be a
miracle if you if you don't if you're
not self-loathing by the time you're 22
the system has to be reformed but who's
going to do it? That's the problem. I
don't blame those people. These are our
people. It's not their fault that they
have this self-loathing inferiority
complex in them. It's not their fault.
This was done to them by the system. If
they had passed through a better
education system, they would not have
any self-loathing,
right? They are just trained to see the
worst of India in everything. This
thing, this good thing happened. But
look at the per capita GDP. We are now
number four economy. But look at the per
capita GDP. Subsaharan Africa. They will
always see the worst in every situation.
Why are they like this? Because they've
been indoctrinated. They've been
trained. They been brainwashed and they
can't overcome the brainwashing. It is
not their fault. It's it's just tragic
that the situation exists. The biggest
problem I agree with you Arun, the
biggest problem is this inferiority
complex, the self-loathing.
But we have to address what causes this
instead of addressing the people who are
suffering from it. Of course, that also
something should be done to maybe make
them see a different perspective. We can
all try. But the real
solution to the problem is to reform the
system that causes this. You see, you
know, who's going to bite the bullet?
Who's going to bell the cat? Who's going
to throw more cliches?
Millerin says, "We need this government
for India's strong foreign policy and
growth. Sadly, many mock foreign trips
is a waste of taxpayers money in the
name of lo local issues. Is this
narrow-mindedness of Indians? This is
this is just another example of the same
inferiority complex. And and it's so
easy for Indians to be to be misled
by maybe the media, maybe by some some
politicians possibly hypothetically,
right?
Indian government officials need
they have legitimate reasons to go on
foreign trips for diplomatic reasons for
trade talks for a variety of things. It
is important, it is vital, it's
essential for India that these trips
happen.
You will see so many foreign delegates,
officials, ministers, etc. coming to
India all the time.
I mean, if you see the schedule in
Delhi, you will see there are foreign
visits all the time. Are they also
wasting their taxpayer money? It's not
the case. I'll tell you what the real
problem is.
The central government when its
officials are going across the world and
engaging with various countries they are
doing it for the national interest. But
it is possible that hypothetically in
some states hypothetically
it is hypothetically possible that maybe
in X state or Y state perhaps
potentially
some MLA delegations may have gone on a
foreign trip hypothetically and use the
taxpayer money to go on these
hypothetical foreign trips and done
nothing and just use it as a sightseeing
visit
and hypothetically it may be happening a
lot hypothetically.
So when you have this hypothetical
situation where there's a pattern of
hypothetical politicians doing this all
the time, then it is natural for Indians
who have been seeing this hypothetically
for decades to be suspicious of all
foreign trips. So can we blame Indians
for that? Even when you have an honest
government hypothetically who is doing
the trips for the right purposes,
Indians are used to seeing this horrible
thing, they will naturally see it the
same way.
So I understand why many genuine people
are very skeptical of all of this and
and that's why it's so easy easy to
mislead them by the very people who have
been doing this.
Right? It's not narrow-mindedness of
Indians. Yeah, maybe it's not. See, when
you are suffering from something for
such a long time and when something
different happens here, you will tend to
not see it differently, right? Because
you are be it's your taxpayer money
that's being wasted hypothetically like
this for decades by these by these
people. So, you will naturally see it
that way. It is very difficult for for
most people to differentiate that this
was the wrong thing but these people are
doing for for the right reasons. It's
very hard to understand that.
So that's why many people mock foreign
trips especially the those with with
self-loathing and inferiority complex
and all that. Yeah. It's it's
unfortunate.
Rutik Yaduanchi says, "What leverage
does is Israel have over the US?" Well,
what leverage does Israel have over the
US?
Uh it is said that there's a very
powerful Jewish lobby in the US. Uh I am
not saying this. Professor John Mir
Shimemer has written Mir Shimmer. Mir
Shimemer, he's written a whole book
about this about the Israel lobby in the
US or something.
So according to that thesis
uh there's a very powerful Israeli lobby
in the US. A lot of very powerful Jewish
politicians, business people etc. who
who advocate for better relations with
Israel and for uh a relationship that is
very pro-Israel.
So maybe that's one of the reasons why
the US has consistently had a very
strongly pro-Israel policy. the the the
the
state the stance in the US is that
Israel is our number one ally. We will
never do anything that will be
detrimental to Israel's interests.
That's that's been the policy of the US
for I would say many years. Right. Is it
because of leverage or is it because a
lot of very prominent powerful rich
Jewish people are in powerful positions
in in the US and they lobby for Israel?
That could be a contributing factor
perhaps. So, professor John Mir framer
has written this book about the Israel
lobby in the US that kind of seeks to
explain why Israel is given this very
preferential treatment by by the US
government. Whichever US government is
in power, they still give very pref
preferential treatment to Israel. Maybe
that explains it.
polarize says but it is believed that
European families have money and it's
managed by this black clock black rock
types and Soros types are front faces
um that's possible
it's possible yeah sure but what's the
question
types could be could could be the front
of the thing maybe it's just the face
maybe soros is just the face of
something much bigger They're much more
powerful. It's possible. Yes. But do I
have evidence of that?
Do I have evidence of it? Do I have
proof that I can show you that? Yeah,
you are right. So, Ross is just a
puppet. He's just a figurehead and so
and so and so and so, so and so, so and
so people have the real money and the
real power and they are using him as a
puppet. Do I have any evidence to prove
it? I don't. Right? So, that's why I
will not speak about it because I have
no evidence.
Kajor Peter Thornon says, "Would
Pakistan betray their old daddy to
please the one who spoils them more? If
the US asks for terrorist attack in
Shinjang, would they facilitate? What
would each side gain or lose if this
happened?" The US will never ask for a
terrorist attack in Shinjang. The US is
a sensible country. They understand what
games are to be played and what games
are to be avoided.
The US is not going to ask going to test
Pakistan's loyalty by asking them to do
to commit suicide.
You understand Pakistan is not to be
used as a tool against China.
The purpose of Pakistan is to be you is
that it can be used as a tool to offset
and counterbalance India and to bleed
India on demand and keep an eye on Iran.
And Pakistan can be a useful way to get
information about China. Pakistan will
never be used to launch terrorist
attacks on China.
The US is a very sensible country. They
know exactly in what ways to use which
asset.
Asking Pakistan to launch terrorist
attack in Shinjang is asking Pakistan to
commit suicide. Won't happen. Right?
Doesn't make it doesn't make any sense.
General Subutai says
uh are we are we seeing the US doing
what UK did in Manipur? Illegal
immigrants pattern is the same longer
consequence.
Okay. Are you talking about what's
happening in Manipur or are you talking
about what's happening in the UK? I
think you're talking about what's
happening in Manipur. So what did the UK
do in Manipur? What did the British do
in Manipur? See
Manipur was under Burmese occupation for
seven years. Horrible Burmese occupation
in the first quarter of the 19th century
because the previous king was super
focused on cultural enrichment on
developing this beautiful manipuri
culture that we have today right the
vishnav culture but he kind of messed up
his succession. So when he died his sons
fought each other for the throne and the
security of the kingdom was completely
neglected. So the Burmese stepped in and
they conquered Manipur and Burma and
Manipur the two kingdoms have had long
long issues going back centuries. Any
any two neighbors have that. So the
Burmese took the opportunity and
occupied Manipur and devastated Manipur
for 7 years. Then
well then the British somehow entered
the picture. I'll not go into the whole
history. It will take a long time. Then
the British come into the picture and
they essentially say that we will
guarantee Manipur's security.
We will we will facilitate the treaty of
Yandabo between Manipur and Burma the
two kingdoms which will and the
guaranter of the treaty will be will be
Britain and that was the process of the
vasalization of Manipur as well as Burma
essentially. It took decades to happen
but that was the beginning of the
process. So then the in the kingdom of
Manipur it was required that the king of
Manipur should have a British political
officer in the court and that was the
beginning of the interference and
eventually in 1891 there's a Anglo
Manipuri war in which the Manipuris were
defeated and Manipur was then physically
occupied and to punish the Manipuris the
mates for daring to fight the British
the British started started settling
foreign tribals into Manipuri territory.
cookies who are now called cookies.
So the even in 1900 the cookie percent
population of Manipur was less than 1%
probably I don't remember the exact
figures I may be wrong about this but it
was a very small percentage but by 19 by
it was significantly larger and the
British confined the mate to 7% of the
land of their own kingdom
and they settled all these outsiders all
across other parts of Manipur mainly the
southern and eastern parts of Manipur.
So they ghettoized the matees, punished
them brutally,
brought in foreigners and that's where
the cookie problem starts. They are
foreigners. They're not Indians. And
after 1949 when Manipur became part of
India, the Indian government, the Nuvian
government did what the British did
because the British were always right.
So they allowed more and more cookies to
come into Manipur. And in the past
decade, I don't know how many lakhs have
come in because the border is open.
Right? That's the situation. Now, how
did suddenly this huge flood of cookies
come into Manipur in the last 10 years
or so? Well, somebody's pushing them in.
And that's where the issue is, right?
So if you want to destroy, if you want
to destabilize a country, take the
border states and flood them with
illegal immigrants, especially those
whose culture is opposed to yours. Those
who don't have any allegiance to your
country or its culture or its
civilization who are enemies
essentially. So yeah, so this is a
spillover of the civil war in Burma. Bur
the Burmese government, the Burmese
military government is not in control of
the whole of the country. It's a proxy
war going on between the US and China in
Burma. And behind this could be rare
earths.
And of course if if this has a bad
spillover effect on India, well even
better. You're killing two stone two
birds with one stone if the US will see
it that way. So that is project K cookie
land for Christ. A creation of of
artificial Christian nation cookie
nation out of parts of Burma, Manipur,
Mizoram and parts of Bangladesh as well.
Now Bangladesh is exempt because
Bangladesh is now a US vasal. So
Bangladeshi territory will not be taken.
But they want to create a de facto
cookie cookie
ruled region in Manipur and Mizoram and
also parts of Burma. Right? So that is
what's being done. So yeah, it's a
continuation of the of what the British
tried and executed and and achieved.
Inferno Jesus says, "Hypothetically, if
India cancels the H1B, can give can the
US give those key resources citizenship
to protect its technoeconomic interests
as a counter move?
It'll be hard to sell that to the
American population." See, who are
Trump's core voter group? It's the MAGA
Americans. Make America great again.
They hate brownies. They hate brown
people like us. They hate Indians.
They're super racist. Many of them. Not
all. Not all but many of them are super
racist
and Trump is failing and he wants to
blame his failures on India. Ukraine
hasn't happened. I I no ceasefire has
happened because it's it's New Delhi's
war. Modi is fighting the war apparently
now and that's why Trump has failed. It
is Modi who has prevented Trump from
doing a ceasefire apparently. So blame
everything on India. If the US economy
is not doing well, blame Indians. These
Indians, these H-1B people, they come
and take our jobs and that's why
Americans don't have jobs. Blame
everything on Indians. Now, let's say
India cancels the H-1B visa program
and requires that all H-1B visa holding
Indians need to come back to India
within let's say 7 days or 15 days. That
will be a disaster for the US tech
industry. It'll the the tech
sector. It'll fortune 500
companies. So, what does the US do
then? Does the Trump regime do a U-turn
and say no no no we need these Hundi
guys? How do they do it? Right? How do
they sell it to their public? So it'll
be it will be a very difficult position
that they that Trump will be in if India
does this cancels unilaterally the H1B
program and asks everybody to come back.
If Trump says that okay I'll give them
all citizenships or green cards then he
will have to face the wrath of his
people. That's the that's the problem
Trump will face if India takes this
step.
Sergeant Skyland says, "I'm surprised by
how much India is getting covered
covered in the international news. So
what is really the alternative to the US
market for now?" Yeah. See, today the
problem for the West is that India is
impossible to ignore now. It's the
fourth largest economy in the world. In
a few months, it will be the third
largest economy. How do you ignore a
nation like that? You may not like that
nation. You may hate them, but how do
you ignore them? That's the problem. So
that's why there's a lot of coverage.
mention most of the coverage is negative
of course right but the coverage is
there earlier India was never mentioned
now they have to mention India and Trump
is doing a very public blaming of India
for everything right uh so that's why
there's so much coverage in the
international news but most of it is
negative now what's the alternative to
the US market so right now look if if
you look at the cumulative trade between
India and the US it's about 90 or
hundred billion dollars roughly give or
take something that's not a lot of trade
we are not exporting a lot to the US. So
if the market is off limits to us
suddenly for so for for whatever reason
it should not be very hard to find
alternatives. Why can't we manufacture
products for Russia for the EU? Why
can't we do it for other countries? So
what are the alternatives? One is the
Russian market. One is the European
market. The European market is bigger
than the Russian market. It has deeper
pockets. So EU but if the US arm twists
the EU into no longer trading with
India, then what does India do? Then
there's Russia. China is not a market
that needs imports. It's an
export-driven market. They have an over
capacity for manufacturing. So, China is
no long even if there's good relations
with China, still what do we export to
China? China has everything. So, then
the solution is to become a consump
consumption-driven economy, lower taxes
for the citizens so that they can
consume more, they can buy more. So, we
produce, we manufacture and our own
people consume. That's another
alternative for that. India the Indian
middle class the Indian all the classes
will need deeper pockets so that will
need a lot of reforms
that's a great opportunity to to do to
do deep reforms in India
daily thank you very much thank you
okay we almost at 2 hours so I'm going
to stop soon
says Europeans say Russians are modern
Mongols who want and are ready to
overrun the whole of EU but also many
said they are losing and falling and
failing in Ukraine. What are my
thoughts? Yeah, this is shingers Russia.
It is winning and losing at the same
time. It is dangerous and helpless at
the same time. It can destroy the whole
of Europe, but it is al also being
defeated by Ukraine at the same time.
Decide one, right? Decide what what the
truth is.
They say that the Russians are not
Europeans, they're not whites, they are
Asiatics, they're Mongols or whatever.
Tatars, whatever.
That's the situation. What are my
thoughts? Russia is
Russia is winning the Ukraine war. The
war is going exactly the way they want.
I don't think Russia has any intention
of overrunning Europe. I don't think so.
But if you want to augment the military
might of NATO, you have to claim that
Russia is preparing to overrun Europe.
That way you can justify higher
uh higher spending for NATO to
militarize NATO more to militarize
Poland more for example right so I don't
think I don't see Russia failing I don't
see that the war is going badly for
Russia the war is going exactly the way
Russia wants Russia is getting stronger
its economic its economy is getting
stronger its industry is getting
stronger one issue it's facing is that
it is very much aligned with China which
is not a comfortable position for Russia
it is to some extent a little more
dependent on China than they would like
to be. So that's why they would like to
have
India rising more. So that is where we
are right now.
Sasput Jenna says why what would the US
do if Japan tries to revolt? They will
crush the revolt through military force
and they will not need to send a
military across the Pacific Ocean to
Japan. The US military is already placed
in Japan. They can crush any revolt
brutally.
Virma, thank you so much. Thank you so
much. Appreciate it.
AVM says, "As India rises, it will be
even harder to control demographic
changes within. How do we reconcile to
be a civilizational superpower?"
As India rises, it will be harder to
control demographic changes within. I
think as India rises and becoming
becomes a more powerful military and
econ economic power, whoever is at the
helm of India
will be in more of a position to prevent
foreign interference in Indian
demographics.
As India gets more powerful, it will be
easier to control
foreign
domest demographic interference in
India. It'll get easier, not harder. The
more powerful you are, the larger you
are economically, the more powerful you
are militarily, the more control you
have internally and the more you can
prevent outsiders from interfering.
So, it's going to be the opposite thing.
Right now, India is a weak country
comparatively. That's why we still have
all these billions of dollars flowing
into India for for industrial scale
conversion activities
and various other such efforts and
projects that are going on in India. By
the time we become a $10 trillion
economy, we'll be able to stop that.
Right now, we are too weak to stop that
apparently. Right? So that's how you
become a civilizational superpower by
rising economically and militarily. That
way you are you have more
strength to control what's happening
within and you can take tougher action
within stronger harder action within uh
to counter
and block
whatever forces may exist that are
trying to
mess with the demography of India and
culture of India and civilization of
India.
Disha Prusti says Disha Prusti says
the Japanese prime minister has
resigned. What are my thoughts on the
reason? The Japanese prime minister has
resigned because Japan has been
humiliated by the US. What humiliation
you ask? Right. The Americans have
forced a very unequal and humiliating
trade deal on Japan.
Um they're going to impose 15% tariffs
on Japan. I think Japan is going to
impose a lower tariff rate on the US. I
don't remember if it was 10% or
something, but the but there's going to
be a gap. So the US will have heavier
tariffs in Japan, but Japan will have
lighter tariffs in the US. So it's
already unequal there. It's already
humiliating here because any trade
agreement has to be reciprocal. It has
to be balanced. But this is imbalanced
already. But that's not the end of the
story. Japan additionally
will invest $550 billion
in America.
So that money will be taken out of
Japan's pocket. It will be invested in
America. How will it be invested? So
since it's Japanese money, Japan should
decide that which industries, which
companies to invest in. No, Donald Trump
will decide.
So you understand what happens. Donald
Trump is going to take his hand, put it
in Japan's pocket, pull out $550 billion
and decide how that money will be used.
I mean, can you imagine more humiliation
than this? That is why I'm glad he only
resigned. The Japanese have other
traditions when they get when there is a
situation of humiliation, they do
something else. I'm glad he has only
resigned.
So now somebody else will be the prime
will be the prime minister and that
unfortunate person will have to
operationalize
will have to operationalize this
humiliation and take it to its logical
conclusion. So that's why dish the
Japanese prime minister has resigned.
Ritwick says explain in brief who are
mythi what the matei naga who are the
cookie who are the actual outsiders.
What has to do with all of this? What is
our geopolitical relation with Myanmar?
How will it affect our future? Okay, let
me try and explain in very brief. We
know something. We know a state called
Manipur. It's got a very old history.
It's it's got a chronicle of kings,
written chronicle of kings that goes
back 2,000 years at least, maybe 4,000
years. Very ancient tradition and
history Manipur has had. It's a kingdom,
right? They have their own system of
writing. They have their own language,
the Manipuri language, all of that. And
they have all these kings, a whole
lineage of kings of the Ninguja dynasty.
Now ask yourself this question simple
and you can fact check it yourself.
Don't rely on me. The Manipuri language
that everyone knows.
Which ethnic group is the originator of
the Manipuri language? Is it the
cookies? Is it the Nagas? Is it the
mates? It is the Matees. This language
is more than 2,000 years old. Manipuri
dance. It's one of the most beautiful
classical dances of India. Right?
Which ethnic group is the originator of
the Manipuri dance? Is it the Nagas? Is
it Matees? Or is it the cookies? It is
the Matees,
not the cookies, not the Nagas. Manipuri
language, matees, not the cookies, not
the Nagas,
right?
And if you look at the kings of Manipur,
more than at least 2,000 years of of
recorded kings we have of Manipur.
What ethnic groups did what ethnic group
did these kings belong to?
Naga, cookie, matey. All of them were
matey.
So Manipur
is
matey. The Matees are are the true
Manipuris and the Nagas also. See the
Naga term was superimposed by the
British.
In Manipur the kingdom which was much
larger than what it is today. You had
the major group was the Matees and you
had all these other clans and tribes who
lived in the hilly parts of Manipur.
They all had different tribal names.
the the pythami,
the the the the Mao, the Tangul and so
on. These are all different tribal
groups and they all have different
languages. Some of these languages are
not even mutually intelligible. But the
British Christianized them all and put
them into one category, Nagas.
Okay. So the Nagas, the people who are
called Nagas are also indigenous to
Manipur
and they are closely related ethnically
to the Mateis.
Okay, their cookies are the foreigners.
They are the outsiders. They came from
somewhere in Yunan or something a few
centuries ago. They are even not even
indigenous to Burma. They are foreigners
even in Burma. They don't speak the
Burmese language. They don't practice
Burmese culture. They don't respect
Burmese culture.
They don't owe any allegiance to Burma
or its culture or its civilization.
Understand this please.
Okay, even these basic facts people are
being misled about by the Indian by
various factions in the Indian media and
various Indian influencers and who knows
what else.
Let's be very clear about these facts.
Please fact check what I just said. Look
it up even okay Wikipedia now may be
lying about this possibly but do proper
facteing from primary sources. Look at
British records themselves. Okay. Best
source is British records.
In 1900, what was the the the cookie
population of Manipur? Must be 1% at at
best. Today, the cookies are possibly a
majority. Now, what happened? Where what
happened? It was all artificially
engineered.
Okay. So, understand who the natives of
Manipur are. It is the Matees and the
Nagas. The cookies are foreigners.
They're not Indians. Today, they may
have other cards and what not. Even
Bangladesh are given other cards now.
Okay. It doesn't mean that they are
Indians.
Uh what's our geopolitical relation with
Myanmar? How will it affect our future?
India has neglected Myanmar for decades.
India neglected all foreign affairs
except for for Pakistan. For decades
after 1947
now our relationship with Myanmar is
decent. We are on decent terms with the
Myanmar government. But for for so many
decades because India was indifferent
towards Myanmar. Myanmar made stronger
relations with China
and China seeks Myanmar's resources like
rare earths and all that and the
Americans want that now. That's why
there's a civil war there
and that's not the only reason for the
civil war. The Americans want a regime
change in Myanmar so that they can put a
puppet government there and use that to
destabilize India just like Bangladesh
and East Pakistan, West Pakistan. That's
the deal.
Okay.
She says, "Was it a strategic failure of
Russia to sell Alaska to the US in
pennies since it's so packed with
natural resources
in the 19th century when the sale
happened? Neither the Russians nor the
Americans knew that there was something
called natural resources in Alaska.
The Americans considered this purchase
of Alaska to be stupidity.
They mocked the American president of
the time who who agreed to the sale and
who purchased the land. The American
media and the American public mocked the
American president.
It was just wilderness, forests and
bears and salmon fish and whatnot.
Nothing. It's only later that all the
oil and gas and other mineral reserves
resources were were discovered. The
Russians also had no idea. And for
Russia, it was just too far. Just too
far. How far can you go from Moscow
further and further and further east?
You're going to cross the the bearing
straight now. They also had Alaska. It
did not make sense at that time for
Russia to hold on to Alaska. If they
knew what was there the way we know
today, they would have not given it up.
Right? So it was not a strategic failure
from using the best information they had
at the time. They said it makes sense to
sell it off to the Americans. We don't
need it. So I would not blame them for
it.
Prattab VGM says China's cities are very
closer
China cities are very closer N CMP to
Indian Y
let me try and understand what's being
asked China cities are very closer and
CMP to Indian why
are they close to each other in
comparison to Indian cities what are you
asking sir I'm I'm very sorry I'm not
able to understand exactly what you're
asking here
China cities are very closer N C in
comparison to Indian
I I'm sorry I I really apologize I would
love to ask you answer your question but
I'm not able to get it I apologize sir I
really apologize could not understand
okay
Jrit Singh says these deadly
catastrophic events we are facing every
year what can we do about it I think we
need a dedicated ministry for natural
disasters
You mean the flash floods and all of
that? Maybe we should have a dedicated
ministry for natural disasters. What can
we do about it? I'm not sure. Can we
predict the some catastrophic cloud
burst somewhere? Can we predict
earthquakes? It's it's next to
impossible to do that. So all you can do
is to be in a state of everpresent
readiness.
So maybe you we should have in every
state a task force a disaster rel I
think we have a national disaster relief
force but does every state have one has
does every state have one located within
the state itself? Maybe we can do that.
So there so there are some states where
natural disasters are more frequent
compared to other states. Some states
are more prone to earthquakes states
near the Himalayan belt. So you can have
something specific to those states
stationed there. So things like these
could be done. If you look at Odisha,
you you have cyclones every year. If you
look at Assam, you have floods every
year. Um
and so on. Yeah. So depending on each
state and its in its uh and and and the
threats it faces, natural threats it
faces. I think every state can have some
contingency measures always ready. That
sort of thing we can do. But can we
predict earthquakes? Can we predict
cloud burst freak cloud cloud event? I
think it's very hard to do that unless
we have a network of radars weather
radars all over the country in every in
every district essentially which is very
expensive. It's a little u unlikely to
happen. So I would say that's what we
could do.
Abhinav Kulkarni says what's hap what
the hell is happening in UK absolute
social fallout.
You mean the immigration thing? Well,
they they they engineered this
themselves, right? So, what can you say?
They're going to pay the price for it.
Eisen says, "What was the difference
between ancient Chinese and Barata in
selecting the bureaucrats? While we know
Chinese and Koreans conducted these
massive exams for the official posts in
the imperial court, the Indian system
and the Chinese system were very
different. The Chinese, you are
absolutely right. They had these
bureaucratic exams. Every year there
would be a exam in which students from
all over the country will come and they
will they will prepared a lot for that
and their great deal the great dream for
the students was to become a highranking
bureaucrat in the Chinese government
machinery. So they would have these
exams and the the the ones who would
pass the exams would would go on to
become bureaucrats. That's how it was
done in China until the Chinese civil
war and revolution destroyed everything.
Um in Bharat in the Bharatya system we
every every king had a council of
ministers
and the council of ministers was chosen
from
it was chosen from the people who were
essentially part of the education system
the wise people. So the Indian education
system was
was completely decentralized.
It was at the grassroots level. It was a
temple based education system. Every
town, every village would have a temple.
Every temple you would have
the the local um priest, let's say
priest would not just be a person who
does prayer, but also he would be a
teacher who would teach children the
basics of mathematics and grammar and
itas and history and all that. The basic
stuff, right? And then you would have
higher level schools which were the
mahaviharas and all that. And then you
also had the visha vidales which is the
great universities and you would have
guruguls and all that. So every royal
family will will have its own gurugul
for its own uh princes and princesses
right that sort of thing. So typically
the council of ministers would be chosen
from these gurugul from the vishuvidy
and also from the commanders and various
ministers who the king himself would
appoint. So it was a different system
from the Chinese system and we don't
quite have the details as to what was
the selection selection procedure. I
think the the the ara shastra gives a
good idea to a certain extent of the
kind of system that that you had and the
procedures you would have to appoint
officials at various levels.
So every Indian empire that was
successful and grew to to a great
extent, each of these empires had a very
sophisticated
governance system in which all of these
things were taken care of in extremely
careful manner. Even non-imperial powers
like the sat satwvahanas. So the
satwahanas are considered to be kingdom
not an empire because they did not rule
the whole of the subcontinent. But even
they had a very sophisticated system of
governance in which the best officials
would be selected and there would be
processes for that. But we have kind of
lost how it was done because of the
destruction of our libraries. Right. So
right I I inver inadvertently took a
history question
and if if some people are offended by
that I apologize. I should not have done
that but yeah when I see a question I
just take it. I am supposed to take
geopolitics questions today. So in case
someone is upset, I apologize.
Okay. Droop says Turkeykey's rise in
drones
steel dome defense influence in coasses,
North Africa and Arab world coupled with
rising religiosity looks like Ottoman
geopolitics returning as European
outlets predict predict. Do you see it
that way? Turkey is becoming is is see
first of all understand Turkey is not a
fully sovereign power because it's part
of NATO. It's a member of NATO. There
are people on Twitter who will say that
no Turkey is one of the sovereign
nations. I completely disagree. Turkey
is a member of NATO which means that
Turkey's armed forces or some part of
Turkeykey's armed forces will at some
point in time given the circumstances
come under the command of a non-Turkish
commander. That way it means that you
are not militarily sovereign. Secondly,
Turkey has Turkey has US nuclear weapons
on its soil which are pointed at Russia
and they don't control these nuclear
weapons or the personnel. Once again,
lack of military sovereignty. So, Turkey
is not sovereign but they have imperial
ambitions. Yes, Erdogan has it and
that's why they have become a major
producer of drones and missiles and all
that. Sure. And with US consent they are
playing geopolitical games in North
Africa in Syria and all that. Now Syria
will stop because the the Americans have
a new vasal in Syria a terrorist who is
now president right.
So Erdogan has this big big dream of
recreating the the Ottoman caliphate
that sort of thing. But the question is
who comes after Erdogan? Will the person
will have will that person be as capable
as Erdogan? have will he or she have the
same political agenda
or will that be engineered and something
else will be made to happen like the
Americans often do. So I think it's
still early to say it's it's a little
too early to say that Turkey is going
the Ottoman Empire way once again. It's
it's it's a long way away from that.
Ritiku when she says will Pakistan and
Bangladesh get more Trump admin support
if uh operation Synindhur 2 starts since
US resisted since India resisted US
tariffs how will it affect the region
see if operation Synindhur 2 starts it
will be against Pakistan not Bangladesh
but the US may incite Bangladesh to
create trouble on India's eastern border
very possible
um and if operation synindur 2 starts
which is another war with Pakistan. It
is highly likely that the Pakistanis
will get material support from the US
very likely. So I think the the
Americans have gone fully on the
Pakistani side. If there is a resumption
of hostilities, they will take the
Pakistani side. It's almost a given now.
And you you may have seen that there are
American strategic heavy lift ve
aircraft
uh cargo aircraft that have been
visiting Pakistan air bases the Nurhan
air base like two days ago and
ostensibly it's to
deliver flood relief or or or whatever
disaster relief supplies but you don't
send high ranking generals to to deliver
supplies right so they may be already
sending some
some military equipment to Pakistan at
this point in time. So yeah, it looks
like that.
Shivans says if you just had to, who
would you choose, US or China? I would
choose neither. I will choose India.
Arian Kapoor says, why is PM Modi soft
on the US and Trump? Despite the trough
stance on India and what are India's
short, medium and 100 and long-term
goals for India? How is PM Modi soft on
the US? How? Because he tweeted
something nice and polite
diplomatically. Is that why he's soft?
Is that the reason why you why you think
that he's soft? Is it so? Because Mr.
Modi recently tweeted that yes, Mr.
Trump, you know, India and US should be
friends and we have we want to have
excellent relations with the with the
US. Is that why you said that he is
soft?
So if you are a viewer of this channel,
you should know that there is a gigantic
difference between words and actions.
The US wants India to cave in and become
a a vasal in very specific ways. Open up
your economy. Impose 0% tariffs on
American goods. Open up your
agricultural sector. Open up your dairy
sector.
And if you do that, our dairy industries
will be destroyed. Our farmers will be
crippled and our manufacturing sector
will die. And we will be completely
dependent on American imports.
Mr. Modi has refused to do that. Do you
call that being soft on the US sir?
It's the opposite of that. Uh what are
India's short, medium and long-term
goals on this? Sovereignty, sovereignty,
sovereignty. Short-term remain
sovereign, resist all pressure.
Medium-term grow the economy to 56
trillion. Long-term goals, make it a $50
trillion economy. India should rise to
its natural position in the world, which
is the world's largest economy. That's
what our goals are. Web of Shindai says,
"How can we get P Rachin back?
Is it possible without any warning or
battle?" I think Indians should right
now for the next
several years forget about Pakai.
Work on
growing the economy.
Everybody should work as hard as
possible. India will automatically get
Pachin back once we are at a certain
stage. When we are at a certain economic
size 10 15 trillion by By the time we
are at a $10 trillion economy it'll be
very hard for Pakistan to to withstand
India by the time we are a 15 trillion
dollar economy P will automatically come
back into our lap without a battle
and once we overtake China even aside
and everything else we'll see about that
my point is we don't want to fight for
these things we want these things to
come back automatically for that we have
to become a very powerful economy so
let's stop this obsession with P Ain
let's just work on the economy and
because when the economy grows the
military strength also grows. All right.
All right.
Ankit, thank you so much. Very kind of
you ma'am. Thank you.
Shivanch says, "Lacks of jobs in
Bangalore and
Gurugram GGN. It's stake if the US bans
tech. Are we g gambling them for a few
oil billions that aren't even cheaper
for the corn people?" See, I I
completely understand why you're asking
this. So, the impression has been
created that the Americans are upset
with India because we are buying Russian
oil because it is we getting Russian
Russian oil slightly cheaper than maybe
Saudi oil or whatever. So, if Saudi oil
is $80 a barrel, we getting Russian oil
for $75 a barrel. What is the deal with
this $5? Stop buying Russian oil. Do
what the Americans say and everything
will be fine. That is what many analysts
want us to believe
and because we are being so obstinate
and we are still saying no we will buy
Russian oil that's why the tariffs have
been levied on India 50% and that's why
lacks of job are jobs are at stake
they're at risk now and Indian companies
are also at risk of going out of
business all because Mr. Modi is being
stubborn. That's what you are being
told. Let me explain what the Americans
really want. And some people are saying
that Modi only has to say except that
Trump mediated the ceasefire with
Pakistan and Modi just has to nominate
Trump for a Nobel Prize. That's all we
have to do and all the troubles will go
away. That's what we are being told by
many Indian analysts, many YouTubers,
influencers and so on.
What's the truth?
What is the truth? H I'll tell you what
the US wants. There were all these
rounds of trade negotiations, right,
with between India and the US and a
trade trade deal did not happen. Even
though India was prepared to make many
concessions, why did the trade deal not
happen? Do you know why the Americans
said you need to drop all tariffs
on American imports?
You need to impose 0% tariffs on
American imports. That's number one.
Number two, you have to open up your
agricultural sector for US exports
imports, which means that you should
import American agricultural products in
India at 0% tariff. That will
immediately kill India's agricultural
sector. Third, open up your dairy sector
to American products at 0% tariffs. That
will kill India's Amul, Sumul Dairy, all
other dairies. It will kill everything.
So if you think that a few lakh jobs are
at stake because of the 50% tariffs now
if India accepts the American demands
entire industries will be wiped out. Do
you understand this sir?
So once again I implore you my dear
viewers I implore you I beg you please
don't restrict yourself to super surface
level analysis. Please dig deeper at to
what the truth is really the the truth
really is. Don't rely on people's
opinions.
Do the analysis yourself.
Please do this.
Okay. Prattab. Okay. We are at almost
two and a half hours. Okay. I'm going to
stop very soon now. Please stop taking
super chats. I'm going to end this very
soon. Prattab says Chinese cities are ah
this is what he's asking. I'm sorry I
did not get it the first time. I
apologize. Chinese cities are much
cleaner compared to India. Why I
answered this? Because okay, let me
answer it. I You may have come in later.
I understand. Why are Chinese cities
cleaner to India compared to India?
Because China is an authoritarian
nation. It's a dictatorship.
Everything in China is controlled from
Beijing.
And Beijing is concerned about the image
of China.
Now in India, I promise you that the guy
in Delhi, the man himself is concerned
about the image of India, but he's not a
dictator. He can't tell the municipal
corporation of X city or Y city that if
you don't do what I tell you, I'm going
to have you shot,
right? He can't do that.
So the municipal corporation in X city
or Y city will continue hypothetically
indulging in corruption, neglecting
living standards, neglecting garbage
collection, neglecting beautifification,
neglecting all of that. All the budget
of the m municipal corporation
hypothetically m much of it will be
swallowed
by the corruption and all the roads
which are dug up every year and created
every year hypothetically they will be
done using substandard equip materials
and all the same cycles continues every
year because India is not an
authoritarian nation because New Delhi
cannot put a gun on an official's head
and so that get it done or else do you
understand why it is like
Let's not blame it on the Indian people.
It's the Indian system.
R says, "Orc or makes AI impossible to
scale it to human level." All right,
sir. This is a geopolitics session, so I
will talk geopolitics today. Maybe in a
science session, we can discuss this.
It's an interesting question point
you're raising here. Uh clause and
effect says, "How do the many tribal
populations in India connect to the
broader population in terms of culture
and language? their deities seem to be
local to them. Well, once again, this
kind of is connected to geopolitics
because it is at the heart of the
western efforts to create fissures and
and divisions in India by targeting the
tribals, by targeting these people and
telling them that you are separate and
you have been oppressed for thousands of
years.
See,
India is a very ancient civilization and
there was a pivotal event several
thousand years ago in India. Several
thousand years ago in India, there was a
pivotal event which you could say is was
an inflection point in our
civilizational history. That pivotal
event was the battle of the 10 kings
in which king Sudas standing alone
defeated a coalition of more than 10
clans and exiled them out of India. And
then that was the Vic age, the Rigidic
age where we used to do yagnas and offer
havs to the gods and all that. and the
the the the gods of the Vic age where
Indra and the pantheon of gods that
surrounds Indra.
Now there are so many communities in
India who have all these local gods,
right? They worship a hill, they worship
a set of trees, they worship some
ancestor who is a god to them. So
a social civilizational contract was
done at this time
after the victory of King Sudas and the
contract was that every god is welcome
at the sacrificial fire the havan fire.
They are all our gods. Every god is
welcome. It's not just Indra and and the
other gods that are in the pantheon
around Indra. Every god of every
community in India is welcome at the
fire at the Yagna fire. They're all our
gods.
I think that explains everything you
need to know about India and our culture
and our civilization. That social
contract happened several thousands
years of years ago. The rigida is the
world's oldest known literature.
It was written closer to 6,000 BC than
to 1500 BC. So that's our civilization
and we are all the same people and all
gods are welcome. They're all our gods.
Gil Gurvinder says what's the current
status of bricks? Is it it is it moving
somewhere or just lost here and there?
Is it retali relation between India and
China improving nowadays?
The current status of bricks is is kind
of here and there. We don't have a
common bricks currency. We have a bricks
bank for sure. We have problems between
the three main nations, India, China,
Russia. Not India and Russia, but China,
Russia, China, India. Now, if those can
be figured out and fixed, then bricks
can actually go somewhere. Thus far,
bricks isn't that consequential. It's
consequential in the sense that it's a
coalition of nations that are stand that
are non-western, not necessarily
anti-western, but non-western and the
the cumulative GDP put together is
bigger than G7. So that itself makes
bricks somewhat consequential. But if
the three main players R I see get get
their act together, bricks can become a
whole different beast. So it all depends
on how things go between India and China
to a large extent. Also China and
Russia, China and Russia are still okay.
Russia is very uncomfortable with the
Chinese dominance right now. But it is
what it is. uh so if India and China can
somehow find a way to coexist without
any major issues and and resolve the
major problems that we have then bricks
could become something entirely
different and it could become a real
challenge to the west the western
hegemony
Jazz Singh says what if China tries to
invade from Uttarakhand what will happen
because it is not spoken about a lot
media doesn't talk about Uttarakand
look the media
the media will focus on whatever
gets the TRPs whatever is most
sensational the media will talk about
that
I'm sure the armed forces
are not the media right the media will
focus wherever they feel is right to
focus the armed forces are professionals
in charge of the safety and security and
territorial integrity of India and they
will look at every square kilometer of
India and all the potential places from
which a hypothetical invasion if it ever
happens could possibly happen from.
So it doesn't matter if the media
doesn't speak about it. The media
doesn't defend the country. The military
does. Now I assure you the military has
everything under control.
Sedhart says why do Indian cities look
uglier than in some warned countries
like Iraq, Libya, Syria, etc. Even Congo
and like roads, basic infrastructure. I
think I answered this question just a
while ago. Let me reanser it.
compare with China. Forget about Yes,
sure. Congo, all that.
China is a dictatorship. It's it's an
autocracy. In China, the government
Xinping is concerned. He he he cares
about the appearance of China. He cares
about the image of China. And therefore
if any municipal corporation in some
small city in China or medium city in
China if they indulge in corruption and
they neglect
living standards and the they neglect
beautifification and the appearance of
the city the members of the municipal
cooperation
something terrible will happen to them
legally
death sentence which is executed within
30 minutes
that's why China is take taken care of
very well. Cities are beautified.
Roads are are perfect,
flat, no floors, there's no garbage
littering around because there are
consequences for these things in India.
If a hypothetical municipal corporation
neglects all these things, are there any
consequences?
There is your answer why it is like
this.
R says China's 40 to 60% GDP is fake by
nightlight analysis. That's what many
economic analysts say. Uh maybe it's
true. I am not an economic analyst so I
can't say it's it's possible for sure.
Mr. Independent Variable says US can
replace Indian H1B with the other
countries easily. Well, good for them.
All the best sir.
Shraan says what are the what is the
geopolitical relevance of letting IDF
soldiers do a soft take off over of
India Tibet border areas of Himachal and
Kasol and Utarakand?
I am I am not aware of this.
I am not aware of this. So I won't be
able to answer this.
IDF Israel Defense Forces really.
Uh so if like I said I'm not aware. I'll
have to look into this if if it's the
case. Yeah.
Apura Adity Ja says longtime viewer.
Appreciate your work. Thank you so much
Apurw. I really appreciate your message
and your contribution. Thank you so
much. Thank you so much.
Shivan says, "Why does the government
has such high tariffs on graphic cards
when they are the backbone of building
LLMs? We anyways don't have any local
manufacturers." Anyways, maybe the
government should look into this. Yeah.
Yeah. And uh yeah, we need to have local
manufacturers too, but as long as we
don't have those, I think uh yeah, then
the tariffs should not be that high. I
think the government either it has a
real good reason for it or maybe they
need to look into it. So, I'm glad that
you are raising this point, sir.
Better thorn says, "What utility does
Russia's one and only Vasal Belellerus
provide? What do they get in return?"
Belellerus gets the security of the U of
the of the Russian military umbrella and
nuclear umbrella.
It gets economic aid.
Its president
gets the benevalent support in Ashirad
of President Trump that you can stay
president as long as you want. I'll take
care of you. And Barus also gets to
station Russian nuclear warheads in
forward locations which will also
safeguard Belarus from a potential NATO
advance in the future. So you see it's
it's it's kind of a win-win thing. So
Barus for that has to kind of subjugate
itself to to Moscow. It is not entirely
sovereign obviously, but the Belarus
people Barusian people and the Russian
people are the same ethnicity. So it
doesn't really matter. Putin is not
going to uh is not going to oppress the
people of Belarus. He's not going to
treat them like secondass citizens. They
are treated just like Russian citizens.
They are treated with respect and with
an equal status. So I think it's a
win-win relationship. And so so it has
it works on multiple levels in this
manner.
Vinci
Vinci I'm sorry it's an unusual name.
I'm sorry if I'm pronouncing it wrong,
but thank you very much. Thank you very
much. I really appreciate that.
Cause and effect says, "What are your
thoughts on automation and AI in
international policy making through an
economic lens?"
automation and AI in international
policy making through an economic lens.
Well,
automation and an AI AI international
pol see automation and AI is not in the
domain of international policym the fact
that automation and AI has entered so
many sectors
that affects the kind of policies
nations can make especially those
nations that have AI and automation. So
if you are the US and you are talking
about the year 2005
then your policy will be different
because you do not have AI or that level
of automation at your disposal.
But now that you have AI and you have
automation you can factor all of that
into your into your policies
international policies military
policies. So let's say
AI. So now if you want to do let's say
you want to contain Russia
and you're worried about the kind of
response patterns Russia may have you
can war game all of that through AI and
you can then take a call based on the
various scenarios AI gives you with
probability percentages potentially if
if if you have seen my geost strategy
series I give forecasts with pro
probability percentages well AI will
give you a frightfully sophisticated
version of that of what I do manually
Right? So it's going to give you very
very detailed scenarios with detailed
probability percentages and AI can give
you 20 scenarios if you want and then
you can take the top three top three and
base your policy on that. So how to deal
with China in so and so sector or or how
to deal with the South China Sea dispute
in so and so thing or whatever, right?
But we're talking about strategic lens
here. Economic lens well AI can give you
economic forecasts also.
You can look at the major fortune 500
companies in let's say China and uh
based on their
their their performance in the past 5
years or 10 years. AI can model their
their future performance. It can do it
on a sector by sector basis, industry by
industry basis, company by company basis
and it can give you very detailed
forecasts based on possibly possibly
classified information also which can
help you forecast what what's what China
is going to what China's economic
position is going to be like in so and
so quarter so and so year and that way
you can formulate your international
policy towards China from the economic
perspective using the leverage of AI and
so on and automation well that has has
more effect on on the military
especially because you can automate
drones you can automate so many things
but you can also automate industries
entirely so all of these things come
together and create this effect
Dr. Hershawan Mor says C7 Globe Master
in Pakistan. Any speculations? So this
aircraft C7 Globe Master it's an
American aircraft. It visited the
Pakistani Nurh Khan air base I think
yesterday or day before yesterday and
they are claiming that they were
delivering some uh some relief materials
for the floods or whatever has happened
in Pakistan. But if you are sending
relief materials you will say you will
not send a high ranking general with the
relief materials. Right? So most likely
they're supplying some weapons systems
to Pakistan or maybe they are evacuating
nuclear weap warheads from Pakistan.
So if a C C7 appears empty then maybe
it's going to take something back.
So most likely like I've been saying the
the the Pakist so-called Pakistani
nuclear weapons are most likely American
nuclear warheads on loan to Pakistan.
And if some of these warheads were hit
during operation synindor and there was
radiation leakage and whatever the
Americans the Pakistanis will not know
how to how to deal with that. So
Americans will have to contain that.
Maybe they will take some materials back
or whatever. Maybe some warheads back.
I'm not sure but yeah there are all
these possibilities.
Okay let us take one last question for
today. This has been a very long episode
almost 3 hours. Tarun says how did
Afghanistan defeat two superpowers US
and USSR as noted by CIA's graveyard of
empires. even British. What is the
future geopolitics of the of the region?
Afghanistan did not defeat the USA.
Why do people believe the Afghans
defeated the USA? The US was in complete
control of Afghanistan.
They handed Afghanistan to the Taliban
on a silver plate
le. But not for free.
There was a whole set of negotiations,
DHA, right? And the dwa accord between
the US and Taliban has secret clauses
which no one knows. So it was a
negotiated agreement and the Americans
handed over the country to the Taliban
on a silver platter. Afghanistan did not
defeat the USA. The USSR who defeated
the USSR and Afghanistan. It was the US
with the help of the ISI and the
Pakistani terrorists. The Afghans did
not defeat the USSR. It was American
weapons, American ammunition,
American supported terrorists and
mujahedin that defeated the USSR. Please
let's not
fall prey to all these illusions. Okay,
it's not that easy to defeat a
superpower. It's impossible.
All right, we are done for the day.
Almost 2 hours 45 minutes. All right,
it's been a long session.
Okay, I'm going to end it over here.
Thank you everybody for all the
questions. This was fun. I know uh
Amisha is saying I'm I look tired. I
don't really I do 8 hour sessions you
know but anyway anyway all right thank
you so much everybody. This was fun and
uh we'll do this once again next week.
Please uh keep learning keep asking
questions. If if you have the
inclination please read my books. If you
do read my books which are available on
Amazon Kindle please leave some honest
reviews. It will really help me. Anyway,
thank you so much. I really appreciate
all of you. Even if you don't buy
anything, I don't care. Perfectly happy.
Thank you so much for everything and
I'll see you in the next live stream.
Take care. Keep learning. Keep asking
questions. Keep raising your standards.
Keep improving. I'll see you soon. Take
care. Bye-bye.